<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">
    <string name="app_name">Asha</string>
    <string name="asha">asha</string>
    <string name="home">Home</string>
    <string name="home_welcome">Welcome,\nAlthea!</string>
    <string name="app_tagline">You\'re Not Alone</string>
    <string name="article_text">Talking about sex can be difficult for many people, and talking about sexual health problems can be even harder. Bedroom issues like sexual performance and low libido may go beyond the scope of what you would normally discuss with your primary care physician, obgyn, or usual therapist. This is where sex therapists enter the picture — trained professionals who focus specifically on human sexuality and healthy sexual behavior, and who can offer compassionate, researchbacked help while addressing the full range of pertinent psychological, physiological, and cultural factors in play. Think sex therapy could be helpful for you and your partner? Learn more about what sex therapists do and what a typical session may look like. What Is Sex Therapy and What Do Sex Therapists Do? “A sex therapist is a licensed mental health professional who has extensive education and</string>
    <string name="emergency_btn_explanation">If you’re in an emergency sexual harassment situation, tap one of the panic buttons for 3 seconds\n\nThe call button will call your trusted contact\n\nThe camera button will record your situation and it will be your evidence</string>
    <string-array name="category_title">
        <item>Mental\nHealth</item>
        <item>Sexual\nHealth</item>
        <item>Komnas Perempuan</item>
        <item>Law\nExpert</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="article_title">
        <item>What Is a Sex Therapist and How Can One Help Me?</item>
        <item>4 Strange Sex Related Symptoms and How to Handle Them</item>
        <item>5 Tips for Choosing the Best Sex Therapist for You and Your Partner</item>
        <item>Taking Care of Your Sexual Health</item>
        <item>Is It Safe to Have Sex During Your Period?</item>
        <item>The Mysteries of Testosterone</item>
        <item>A HisandHers Sexual Health Issue</item>
        <item>The Link Between UTIs and Sex: Causes and How to Prevent Them</item>
        <item>What Is the Role of Intimacy and Sex in Your Overall Health?</item>
        <item>Fathers Chronic Health Conditions Linked to Pregnancy Loss Risk</item>
        <item>Half of Young Women Are Unhappy With Their Sex Lives, a New Study Reveals</item>
        <item>Contraception Options 101: Everything You Need to Know About Birth Control</item>
        <item>Sex Therapy: What Men and Women Should Know</item>
        <item>How to Have Safe and Satisfying Sex During the COVID19 Pandemic</item>
        <item>Ovarian Cancer and Pregnancy: What You Need to Know</item>
        <item>Ovarian Cancer Pain: What It Feels Like, What Causes It, and How Women Manage It</item>
        <item>Why Is It So Hard to Speak Up About Painful Sex?</item>
        <item>Sex After Menopause: The Psychological Factor</item>
        <item>10 Things Your Doctor Wont Tell You About Hysterectomy</item>
        <item>To Boost Your Sex Life, Try Getting Better Sleep</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="article_author_name">
        <item>Catherine Pearson, Medically Reviewed by Allison Young, MD</item>
        <item>Stacey Colino, Medically Reviewed by Kacy Church, MD</item>
        <item>Catherine Pearson, Medically Reviewed by Allison Young, MD</item>
        <item>Madeline R. Vann, MPH, Medically Reviewed by Lindsey Marcellin, MD, MPH</item>
        <item>Amy Kraft, Medically Reviewed by Justin Laube, MD</item>
        <item>Shanna H. Swan, PhD and Stacey Colino</item>
        <item>Stacey Colino</item>
        <item>Meryl Davids Landau, Medically Reviewed by Kacy Church, MD</item>
        <item>Beth Levine, Medically Reviewed by Allison Young, MD</item>
        <item>Becky Upham</item>
        <item>Becky Upham</item>
        <item>Cheryl Alkon, Medically Reviewed by Kara Leigh Smythe, MD</item>
        <item>Beth Levine, Medically Reviewed by Allison Young, MD</item>
        <item>Kaitlin Sullivan, Medically Reviewed by Kacy Church, MD</item>
        <item>Liz Scherer, Medically Reviewed by Thomas Urban Marron, MD, PhD</item>
        <item>Jessica Migala</item>
        <item>Michelle Konstantinovsky, Medically Reviewed by Kacy Church, MD</item>
        <item>Andrea Peirce, Medically Reviewed by Kacy Church, MD</item>
        <item>Jennifer J. Brown, PhD, Medically Reviewed by Kacy Church, MD</item>
        <item>Meryl Davids Landau</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="article_author_img">
        <item>@drawable/authorimg1</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg2</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg3</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg4</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg5</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg6</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg7</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg8</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg9</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg10</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg11</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg12</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg13</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg14</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg15</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg16</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg17</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg18</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg19</item>
        <item>@drawable/authorimg20</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="article_date">
        <item>March 5, 2020</item>
        <item>September 19, 2019</item>
        <item>March 9, 2020</item>
        <item>February 17, 2016</item>
        <item>April 11, 2019</item>
        <item>April 21, 2021</item>
        <item>August 5, 2020</item>
        <item>February 20, 2020</item>
        <item>March 3, 2020</item>
        <item>December 18, 2020</item>
        <item>February 27, 2020</item>
        <item>December 22, 2021</item>
        <item>March 16, 2020</item>
        <item>February 11, 2021</item>
        <item>August 27, 2020</item>
        <item>September 18, 2020</item>
        <item>August 23, 2021</item>
        <item>February 17, 2021</item>
        <item>March 27, 2018</item>
        <item>April 21, 2021</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="article_background">
        <item>@drawable/article1</item>
        <item>@drawable/article2</item>
        <item>@drawable/article3</item>
        <item>@drawable/article4</item>
        <item>@drawable/article5</item>
        <item>@drawable/article6</item>
        <item>@drawable/article7</item>
        <item>@drawable/article8</item>
        <item>@drawable/article9</item>
        <item>@drawable/article10</item>
        <item>@drawable/article11</item>
        <item>@drawable/article12</item>
        <item>@drawable/article13</item>
        <item>@drawable/article14</item>
        <item>@drawable/article15</item>
        <item>@drawable/article16</item>
        <item>@drawable/article17</item>
        <item>@drawable/article18</item>
        <item>@drawable/article19</item>
        <item>@drawable/article20</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="article_detail">
        <item>Talking about sex can be difficult for many people, and talking about sexual health problems can be even harder. Bedroom issues like sexual performance and low libido may go beyond the scope of what you would normally discuss with your primary care physician, obgyn, or usual therapist.\nThis is where sex therapists enter the picture trained professionals who focus specifically on human sexuality and healthy sexual behavior, and who can offer compassionate, researchbacked help while addressing the full range of pertinent psychological, physiological, and cultural factors in play. Think sex therapy could be helpful for you and your partner? Learn more about what sex therapists do and what a typical session may look like.\nWhat Is Sex Therapy and What Do Sex Therapists Do?\n“A sex therapist is a licensed mental health professional who has extensive education and training in sex therapy in addition to mental health,” says Neil Cannon, PhD, a Coloradobased sex therapist who serves as bylaws chair for the American Association of Sexuality Educators, Counselors, and Therapists (AASECT).\nThere are many different paths people can take to becoming a sex therapist. A sex therapist might be a psychologist or psychiatrist, a clinical social worker, a family therapist, or maybe a doctor or nurse who has psychotherapy training and who has gone on to get specialized training in sexuality and sexual functioning, intimacy, and relationships.\nThose are big, broad buckets, of course. But a qualified sex therapist should be adept at addressing a wide range of concerns including (but by no means limited to): issues about sexual desire, ejaculationrelated problems, trouble orgasming, painful sex, and more.\n\nWhat a Session With a Sex Therapist May Look Like\nSex therapy varies significantly depending on what is being addressed and who the therapist and patient — or patients — are. So there is no standard answer for what a particular therapy session might entail or how often you will go. One thing that will not be a part of any sessions is sexual contact. Sex therapy is talk therapy.\n\nMost sex therapists will start by getting a thorough picture of your sexual history, whether they ask for that information before you attend a session, in person, or both.\n\n“You’re really getting a sense of what, historically, has shaped a [patient’s] sexual map or preferences,” explains Megan Fleming, PhD, a clinical psychologist and sex therapist in New York City. “And then, most importantly, what is their presenting challenge or complaint that they want to be working on.”\n\nA sex therapist will consider what Dr. Fleming calls the “biopsychosocial” determinants contributing to a client\'s concern — meaning any potential biological, psychological, and social factors — and will work with you to create a specific treatment plan. Sex therapists may see individuals, couples, or both. Some may be comfortable starting with an individual who eventually brings in his or her partner, though Fleming says that whether a therapist does this will depend on the specific circumstances.\n\nWhat a Sex Therapist May Commonly Recommend\nAgain, the recommendations a sex therapist gives vary dramatically from patient to patient and the issues they are addressing.\n\n“It depends on the therapist you’re working with as well as what it is you’re looking for,” says Fleming. Sometimes you’ll see the therapist for just a handful of sessions, maybe with a tuneup down the road; other times longterm, indepth therapy might be called for.\n\nExpect homework, which can be a common element of sex therapy. Your sex therapist will ask you to complete specific tasks in between sessions, and then ask you or you and your partner to report back. Those homework assignments could range from communication exercises to specific sexual experimentation activities.\n\nWhat Type of Training Does a Sex Therapist Receive?\nUnfortunately, no regulations govern who can call themselves a sex therapist, which is why it is important to pay close attention to credentials.\n\n“In most states, anybody can say that they’re a sex therapist — or that they do sex therapy — and the consumer has no idea whether this person has ever taken a single class, has ever gone through any training, or has been supervised around sex therapy by qualified supervisors,” warns Dr. Cannon. “So if you don’t go to a certified sex therapist, it’s buyer beware.”\n\nAASECT requires sex therapists to have an advanced degree that includes psychotherapy training and a certain amount of clinical experience — plus 90 hours of human sexuality education, 60 hours of sex therapy training, and then extensive supervision by a qualified supervisor.\n\nHow Can I Find a Sex Therapist Near Me?\nAASECT keeps a list of licensed sex therapists on its site, which Cannon recommends as a good starting point. If you live in an area where sex therapists aren’t plentiful, he says teletherapy, or virtual therapy, may be an option.\n\nOther healthcare providers may also be able to help, like your primary care physician or a more generalized therapist who may refer you to a sexual health specialist.\n\nIf you are in a position to, you should feel empowered to shop around for a good fit.\n\n“This is not an easy topic for people to talk about,” says Fleming. “You need to feel that the person is openminded, they’re not judgmental, they’re going to help you explore, and they’re really trying to help you ask the right questions — but they’re not jumping in to diagnose and pathologize.”\n\nRemember: Your sex therapist must be a good fit for you. “Therapy is really about a relationship,” she adds. “So feeling a sense of security and safety — those are really important pieces.”</item>
        <item>Even if you take smart steps to protect yourself from the biggest and most worrisome sex aftereffects — like getting a sexually transmitted infection or ending up pregnant — others can occur that are far less serious but still annoying. Whether it’s because you and your hot lover couldn’t get enough of each other or you had an insanely intense, shoutingfromtherooftops orgasm, you may not feel the way you expected to after all the redhot excitement is over.\n\nThese postcoital hangovers can range from truly rare conditions, such as transient global amnesia after sex (temporary memory loss and confusion, per previous research), which, the Mayo Clinic says, warrants medical attention to rule out more serious conditions; to common ones, such as aftersex leg cramps, according to Planned Parenthood, which can be relieved with some simple stretches or will dissipate on their own.\n\nHere are four other surprising but fairly common aftersex hangovers, with advice on how to handle them:\n\n1. A SexRelated Headache \nYou’ve undoubtedly heard the famous excuse, “Not tonight, dear. I have a headache.” But did you know that headaches could be triggered during sex? It’s true. Headaches, ranging from tensiontype to migraines, can occur during sexual intercourse or orgasm. There are two primary ways this can happen, according to the National Headache Foundation: If you get excited during intercourse, you can experience muscle contractions in the head and neck that can lead to headache; or you could get an intense headache right before having an orgasm, possibly in response to a rapid increase in blood pressure and heart rate.\n\nHow You Might Experience SexRelated Head Pain\n\nFor most people sexrelated headaches, as described by the National Migraine Foundation, are a temporary form of discomfort that may not even happen again. For others, “headaches often recur during sexual encounters for a brief period of time and never return again, whereas others experience them at infrequent intervals throughout their lifetime,” says Brian Grosberg, MD, director of the Hartford Healthcare Headache Center and a professor of neurology at the University of Connecticut School of Medicine in Farmington.\n\nWhat to Do When SexRelated Headaches Happen\nIf you start to get a headache during sex, “stopping the sexual activity or assuming a more passive role can lessen [its] severity,” Dr. Grosberg says. Or, you can treat it with an antiinflammatory drug or a migrainespecific treatment if you’re prone to migraines. If these headaches are a regular occurrence, get them checked out by your doctor.\n\n2. Postcoital Asthma FlareUps\nIf your asthma isn’t well controlled, sexual intercourse could trigger an asthma flareup, just like exercise can — because “sex is like brisk walking,” explains Sandra Gawchik, DO, codirector of Asthma and Allergy Associates in Chester, Pennsylvania. “During intercourse, symptoms such as chest tightness, trouble breathing, coughing, or wheezing can come out of the blue.” In fact, a small study published in February 2019 in BMJ Open Respiratory Research found that severe asthma can have a significant impact on physical and emotional intimacy in sexual relationships, partly because of overwhelming exhaustion and partly due to anxiety that having an orgasm could induce severe bronchospasms and an asthma attack.\n\nHow to Avoid SexRelated Asthma Episodes\nTo prevent an asthma flareup from happening during sex, make sure your asthma is controlled with medication that works for you, and take steps to reduce anxiety about having sex, through biofeedback or mindfulness training, Dr. Gawchik says. “If you don’t treat the anxiety, you’re already set up to have a problem.” Using an adrenergic bronchodilator inhaler (such as Albuterol) before having sex may be helpful, and altering your position may make a difference. “Being on the bottom can be problematic because you’ll have pressure on your chest; try being on top or on your side,” Gawchik suggests. If you don’t know that you have asthma and you have trouble breathing during or after sex, go to the ER. \n\n3. AfterSex Sorrow and Sadness or Mood Swings\nHave you ever felt sad, weepy, or anxious after having sex? If so, you’re no stranger to postcoital dysphoria (aka the postsex blues, per the International Society for Sexual Medicine). It’s a surprisingly common phenomenon: In research published in December 2015 the journal Sexual Medicine, investigators looked at 230 women and found that 46 percent had experienced postcoital dysphoria at some point and 5 percent did frequently. “Postsex sadness, anxiety, or agitation can feel confusing and uncomfortable, especially for those who are used to experiencing pleasure and closeness with their partners following sexual activity,” notes Elizabeth A. Grill, PsyD, an associate professor of psychology at Weill Cornell Medicine and New York–Presbyterian Hospital in New York City.\n\nHow to Handle SexRelated Mood Swings\nFortunately, it’s usually relatively shortlived and you can take steps to ease this emotional discomfort while it lasts by engaging in soothing deep breathing techniques, distracting yourself with a pleasant activity such as listening to music, or talking to your partner about your feelings (assuming you have a close relationship and good communication). The keys to handling the latter the right way are to own your feelings by using statements that begin with “I” (such as “I felt sad when you didn’t hold me after we finished having sex”) and to ask for what you need (by saying, “I don’t need you to cheer me up; I just want you to listen or give me a hug”), Dr. Grill advises. If feelings of postsex dysphoria persist or recur often, it’s a good idea to talk to a counselor or therapist about why it might be happening — and what you can do to get manage them. \n\n4. Honeymoon Cystitis (Urinary Tract Infections)\nIf you’ve experienced burning or pain when you pee, an increase in urinary urgency and frequency, or pinktinged urine after a night of intense sex, you’re familiar with honeymoon cystitis (even if you weren’t on your honeymoon). The symptoms stem from repeated episodes of intercourse, which can cause irritation of the vagina, including microscopic tears in the skin around the vagina and urethra, or inflammation of the lining of the bladder, explains Jill Rabin, MD, vice chair of education and development in obstetrics and gynecology with Northshore University Hospital and LIH Medical Center in New Hyde Park, New York, and author of Mind Over Bladder. These tiny breaks in the skin allow bacteria to enter the bladder, especially if you don’t flush it out by peeing right after intercourse. Similarly, if you have rectal intercourse (anal sex) then vaginal intercourse or you have oral sexual activity, bacteria can make their way into the bladder, she adds.\n\nNo woman is immune to this risk: Research published in the Journal of General Internal Medicine found that sexual intercourse increases the risk of symptomatic urinary tract infections in postmenopausal women, just as it does in younger women. If you develop a fever, body aches, and chills, along with vaginal discomfort, see a doctor ASAP because these symptoms signal infection. If you suspect you’re experiencing irritation of the urinary tract, rather than an infection, using an overthecounter product such as Uristat or Azo can relieve the bladder spasms and pain, advises Dr. Rabin. To hasten your recovery, stay well hydrated to help flush out bacteria and avoid intercourse until symptoms go away.</item>
        <item>There are many reasons why a person or couple might seek out help from a sex therapist. Research shows that an estimated 43 percent of women and 30 percent of men report grappling with some form of sexual dysfunction. But sex therapists can also help with so much more, addressing everything from arousal and attractionrelated issues to boredom — and beyond.\n\nFinding the right fit for you and your partner isn’t always easy. The field is largely unregulated, and the topic is incredibly intimate. Here are five tips to keep in mind when you’re looking for the right sex therapist for you.\n\n1. Ask Yourself: Why Do I Need a Sex Therapist?\nSex therapy is a big field that encompasses everything from desire issues to physical concerns, and while a qualified sex therapist should have a grounding in all of it, it can help to start off by asking any therapist you’re considering if they have significant clinical experience addressing your particular concern (or concerns).\n\nIn order to even ask that question, it is important to try and get clear about why you’re seeking help.\n\n“People should be asking themselves things like, ‘Why therapy? Why now? What is it that we want to work on?’” recommends Megan Fleming, PhD, a New York City–based sex therapist. “And more importantly, ‘What are we prepared to do to achieve those goals?’”\n\nAre you willing to take time out of your schedule or schedules to regularly meet with a sex therapist? Are you open to “homework” — which might include communication exercises, reading or watching educational materials, or sexual experimentation activities — in between sessions? Are you willing to discuss such an intimate topic with someone else — and possibly your partner? These are the types of questions to consider ahead of time.\n\n2. Consider the Therapist’s Credentials and Qualifications\nIt’s important to research whether a therapist you’re considering has real experience and credentials.\n\nCertification through a professional organization for sex therapists requires an advanced degree, like a PhD, an MD, or a master’s degree with some element of psychotherapy training, then 90 hours of human sexuality training, 60 hours of sex therapy training, and extensive supervision by a qualified sex therapist. These therapists are trained to consider the many factors that can affect sexual health.\n\n“[Certified] sex therapists are generally trained to look at problems from multiple dimensions — a physiological dimension, a psychological dimension, a potentially cultural dimension, and certainly a relational dimension,” says Ian Kerner, PhD, a sex therapist in New York City.\n\nOne note: While couples’ therapists may be able to help with some of that, they generally do not have deep clinical experience in sexual issues specifically, Dr. Kerner says.\n\n3. Meet With Multiple Options When Choosing a Therapist\nPeople find sex therapists many ways, whether through a professional organization like the American Association of Sexuality Educators, Counselors, and Therapists (AASECT), a referral from a generalized therapist or physician, from friends, or via an online resource like Psychology Today. Vetting the credentials of any potential candidate is a good first step, but it can also be helpful to meet with multiple therapists.\n\n“I personally think you should try to see two to three therapists for an initial consultation if possible,” says Dr. Fleming, who explains that sex therapists can have very different styles and that it is important that both partners feel comfortable, if you plan on attending with your partner.\n\nAccording to Fleming, sex therapy can be for individuals or couples. Sometimes it is possible to start as an individual and then bring in your partner, though not every therapist will be open to that scenario.\n\nIf you do not live in an area with multiple — or any — sex therapists, teletherapy, or virtual therapy, is an option.\n\n4. Ask About the Therapist’s Treatment Plan and Insurance\n\nAlthough therapy is a dynamic process that can change as you go along, it is totally appropriate to ask any potential sex therapist about what they think your treatment plan might entail and what kind of time commitment they think it will require. It is also fair game to ask about the cost.\n\n“The reality, when it comes to sex therapy, is that many of us — I would dare say most of us — are not on managed care,” says Fleming.\n\nThat does not mean that you won’t qualify for outofnetwork benefits and reimbursement, she adds, but it is something you should discuss with a potential therapist, and your insurer, up front. It has implications not just for your wallet, but for your treatment.\n\n“If you’re stressed about finances, that in itself is going to affect your ability to make the commitment and do the work,” says Fleming.\n\n5. Regularly Check In With Yourself as Therapy Progresses\n\nSex, sexual health, and sexual problems are complex and intimate. You might not feel comfortable discussing them with a therapist, particularly at the beginning. But you should start to feel more comfortable as your treatment progresses. If you don’t, that’s a possible red flag that you and the therapist are not the best fit.\n\n“Most sexual problems are really kind of universal, so you should feel kind of held and normalized — and feel in the end that you’re not so alone, that other people are dealing with this,” says Kerner. “You should feel like you’re with someone who can both explain what is going on and also hopefully relieve some of the mystery, the stress, and the anxiety associated with a sexual problem.”\n\nUltimately, the goal is to get to a place where you can live what Kerner calls an “authentic sex life.”\n\n“It’s really about helping someone to have the kind of sex that will be gratifying to them,” he says, “and for sex to be integrated into their life in the way that they want it to be.”</item>
        <item>Sexual health. For some people any sex topic is offlimits. But others, including the World Health Organization, consider sexual health an essential dimension of human health and wellbeing. From concern over how to have comfortable, enjoyable sex to questions about testing for sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) and their prevention, many important topics come under the broad umbrella of sexual health.\n\n“Sexual health is an essential and beneficial dimension of being human,” emphasizes Michael McGee, MEd, a certified sexual health educator and adjunct professor at Montclair State University in Montclair, N.J. “People have a right to sexual health, sexual health information including public policy that supports sexual health, and the right to pleasure.”\n\nIn addition to teaching and advocating about sexual health, McGee counsels individuals and couples on sexual health issues. He says the most common, fundamental question he encounters is, “Am I normal?”\n\nThis, he argues, is the best reason to be educated about sexual health: to have a realistic understanding of what sexual health is — what the wide range of “normal” is — as well as being better able to take care of your own health and pleasure and that of your partner.\n\nIncrease Your Sexual Health Awareness\n\nPremature ejaculation and a woman’s ability to achieve orgasm are topics that McGee says his clients often worry about — and appreciate learning how to manage. Other aspects of sexual health that people should be educated about include:\n\nSex basics. Understanding the cycle of desire, stimulation, and response improves sexual health, says McGee.\nReproductive issues. Sexual health is intimately related to reproduction. Birth control choices to prevent pregnancy and the steps couples need to take to have a healthy pregnancy are all aspects of sexual health.\nVaginal dryness. As women go through changes in their lives, such as pregnancy and childbirth or menopause, they may experience a lack of vagina lubrication. This makes sexual intercourse unpleasant, but there are solutions to this problem.\nLack of desire. A frequent source of conflict between couples, says McGee, is a “discrepancy in desire — one partner wants sex more often than the other.”\nErectile dysfunction. There are various physical and emotional reasons why men may not be able to achieve an erection for the duration of sexual intercourse.\nPhysical challenges. Physical impairment, health concerns, and other conditions may require creative problem solving in order to have sexual intercourse.\n\nSexual Health: Guarding Against Infection\n\nSex can be pleasurable, but it can also be risky. Sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) can be uncomfortable or painful; they can have severe, longterm effects that include the loss of fertility and have the potential to be lifethreatening. Learning about sexual health means learning about STDs:\n\nSTD identification. Learn about the signs and symptoms of STDs as well as the consequences of infection.\nPrevention. Taking steps to prevent the spread of STDs protects your health and the health of others.\nSTD testing. STD testing is a crucial part of your sexual health plan. Finding out whether you have an STD enables you to start treating the infection and protecting your sexual partners.\nLiving with an STD. Some STDs will be with you for life, such as hepatitis, herpes, and HIV/AIDS. For people living with STDs, sexual health encompasses coping with these infections over the long term.\nIntimate partner violence. Safety within sexual relationships continues to be a concern. Women may be particularly at risk for sexual violence.\n\nHow to Get Help for Intimate Issues.\n\nUnfortunately, many people wait a long time before seeking a solution to their sexual health concerns, notes McGee: “By the time they come to a professional, usually it has become a pressing need. And it is sometimes very difficult.” McGee recommends seeking help as soon as you have concerns rather than waiting and hoping the problem will go away.\n\nMcGee is certified by the American Association of Sexuality Educators, Counselors, and Therapists (AASECT) as a sexual health educator. Depending on the problems you want to resolve, your sexual health team could include a variety of health professionals, such as:\n\nPrimary care doctor\nObstetrician\ngynecologist\nUrologist\nPhysical therapist\nMental health professional\n\nWhether it’s knowledge about your body or information about treating a specific condition, take the right steps to get education and any counseling you might need to protect your sexual health.</item>
        <item>Just because you\’re having your period doesnt mean you have to forego sexual activity. For some women, sex during menstruation can be even more pleasurable than at other times of the month.\n\nThe need for lubrication lessens during your period, and having an orgasm can soothe periodrelated symptoms, such as cramps. Plus, a study published in Cephalalgia concluded that sexual activity may reduce migraine and cluster headache pain for some.\n\n“Sex is a normal part of life and should be enjoyed by all women,” says Carrie Coleman, MD, an ob/gyn at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston. “Basically, ensuring you have good contraception and sexually transmitted infection (STI) prevention throughout the menstrual cycle should make it even more safe and enjoyable.”\n\nBut before having sex, make sure you understand the risks of STIs, other infections, and pregnancy — even during your period.\n\nHere’s what you need to know about having safe sex during your period.\n\nInfection Risk From Sex During Your Period\nIt’s crucial to practice safe sex while you’re having your period because you could still get or transmit an STI, like HIV, during this time, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. The virus may be present in menstrual blood. Therefore, doctors strongly encourage using a condom to decrease this risk.\n\nLauren Streicher, MD, a clinical professor of obstetrics and gynecology at Northwestern University’s Feinberg School of Medicine in Chicago, says that anecdotally speaking, there are two reasons for this risk. “Any bodily fluid can carry HIV or [other] STIs, and [during your period], the cervix opens slightly, which might allow viruses to pass through,” she says. “My message to women is you’re not off the hook as far as using protection.”\n\nYou may also be more prone to some infections in general at this time. Your vagina maintains a pH level of 3.8 to 4.5 throughout the month, according to the American Congress of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG). But during menstruation, that level rises because of the higher pH level of blood, and yeast is able to grow more rapidly.\n\nSymptoms of a vaginal yeast infection are more likely to occur the week before your menstrual period, and intercourse during this time can exacerbate symptoms. But clear evidence is lacking for any increased risk of getting a yeast infection if you have sex during your period.\n\nTheres also the dreaded UTI. “Some women can be more prone to having urinary tract infections after intercourse,” says Dr. Coleman. “This is most likely related to bacteria being able to easily travel to the bladder with intercourse, but it may happen at any point during the menstrual cycle.”\n\nRisk of Pregnancy During Your Period\nYes, you can get pregnant when you have your period, especially if you have a shorter menstrual cycle (21 to 24 days) and you have have sex toward the end of your period. Sperm can remain viable in your vagina for up to five days, so pregnancy is possible, and it’s important to continue to use birth control. \n\nLess Need for Vaginal Lubrication\nYou’re less likely to need lubricants if you engage in intercourse during menstruation, because menstrual discharge tends to provide enough lubrication. If you do need a lubricant, then “waterbased lubricants are widely available and safe both for sex and for condoms,” says ob/gyn James Simon, MD, a clinical professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the George Washington University School of Medicine in Washington, D.C. “Silicone and hybrid lubricants that are waterbased and siliconebased are likewise safe for both sex and condoms. Oilbased lubricants, especially mineral oilbased lubricants, can deteriorate condoms —\nincreasing the risk of breakage — and are not recommended with latex condoms,” he says.\n\nPeriod Sex as a Pain Reliever\nIf you experience symptoms such as cramping, feelings of sadness, or depression during your period, having sex at this time may be beneficial. Dr. Streicher says that because orgasms release endorphins — feelgood hormones like oxytocin and dopamine — in theory they could also decrease some period symptoms. “There’s no harm in trying,” she says.\n\nWomen who have endometriosis, on the other hand, may experience more pain and other symptoms when they have their period, as well as pain that occurs with sexual activity or orgasm. However, treatments are available, and sex doesn’t have to hurt. Talk to your doctor as soon as possible; the earlier you speak up, the sooner you can feel better and enjoy sex again.\n\nSexual Arousal During Your Period\nYou may feel more sexually aroused and sensitive during this time of the month because of the changes in your hormone levels. Some women experience an increased feeling of congestion in the pelvic area, which can also ramp up your sex drive. But for some women, this extra sensitivity may make it uncomfortable to have sex during this time. (If you don’t like having sex when you have your period, there are birth control options that can make your period shorter, lighter, and/or less frequent, or even eliminate your period altogether.) Remember that there’s nothing shameful or dirty about having your period — it’s totally natural, and theres nothing wrong with having sex during that time of the month. The bottom line is to make sure that both you and your partner are comfortable with the situation. “Don’t assume anything,” Dr. Simon says. “Open questions with honest answers beforehand are paramount.”</item>
        <item>Throughout the world, testosterone levels are decreasing, and most people don’t know this or understand the significance of this trend. It’s problematic on multiple levels — for reproduction, health and longevity, libido, and proper fetal development during pregnancy. While researching and writing our new book Count Down: How Our Modern World Is Threatening Sperm Counts, Altering Male and Female Reproductive Development, and Imperiling the Future of the Human Race, we discovered research showing not only that sperm counts and testosterone levels are declining, but they’re doing so in tandem and at an alarming rate of 1 percent per year in Western countries.\n\nAt first blush, this may not sound like a big deal, but it is. It adds up to more than a 10 percent decline per decade and more than a 50 percent drop over 50 years. Meanwhile, rates of testicular cancer and the prevalence of erectile dysfunction have been increasing at a similar rate, and so have miscarriage rates in the United States. It’s not a pretty picture.\n\nIts Not Just About Sperm Counts; Reproductive Health Is Also at Stake\nIt’s noteworthy that the use of testosterone replacement therapy has increased dramatically among younger men, many of whom are taking it to boost their energy and muscle mass. In fact, a study in the April 2017 issue of the Journal of Urology found that the use of testosterone replacement therapy had increased fourfold among men between the ages of 18 and 45 and threefold among older men from 2003 to 2013. What men don’t realize is that with testosterone replacement, a decline in sperm production occurs, so they’re working at crosspurposes with their best interests if they want to have children.\n\nThe Hormone Testosterone Plays a Role in Women’s Health as Well as Men’s Health\nPeople often think of testosterone as a “male” hormone, but girls and women also produce testosterone in their ovaries (in guys it’s made by the testes); however, women produce it in much smaller amounts than men do. In both sexes, the hormone affects energy levels, cognitive function, libido, and sexual function. When women’s lack of sexual desire is persistent and distressing, it’s called hypoactive sexual desire disorder, and according to a consensus statement in a 2019 issue of the NEJM Journal Watch Women’s Health, “Testosterone therapy is indicated only for postmenopausal women with hypoactive sexual desire disorder (HSDD), with evidence suggesting moderate therapeutic effects.” So clearly testosterone plays a crucial role in women’s sexual function, just as it does for men.\n\nFor women, there’s a sweet spot for testosterone levels at various stages of life. Too much or too little can send reproductive health and development in the wrong direction. For example, when a woman is pregnant, in order for her baby to develop properly, it needs to be exposed to the right amount of testosterone in the womb at the right time — it’s the Goldilocks conundrum in play.\nHere’s where things get tricky: Research has found that if a male fetus gets too little testosterone while in the womb, his genitals and his brain are likely to become less maletypical. By contrast, if a female fetus is exposed to too much testosterone in utero — perhaps because she has congenital adrenal hyperplasia, a genetic condition — her brain and genitals will be less femaletypical after she’s born. In other words, exposure to testosterone has the ability to push a developing fetus along the continuum between male and female. Once they’re born and start to grow up, these hormonal effects can influence the way children perceive themselves in terms of gender; what’s more, they can affect the kids’ activity preferences (playing with cars and trucks vs. dolls, for instance) and their style of play (roughandtumble vs. gentle, for example).\n\nIn addition, when girls and women have elevated levels of testosterone — as they do with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), which research suggests is increasing in incidence — they often have irregular periods, fertility challenges (including a higher rate of miscarriages), hair in unwanted places, acne, and excessive weight gain. And if they do have babies, these women’s baby girls are likely to have a higher body mass index (BMI), according to research published in April 2016 in Reproductive System and Sexual Disorders: Current Research.\n\nWhy Testosterone Levels Are Out of Whack\nNow that you know how testosterone levels affect women’s and men’s reproductive health, here’s the shocker: All the reproductive changes that have been occurring in recent years are too synchronous to be a coincidence. These changes are partly driven by poor lifestyle choices (such as smoking, binge drinking, and the like) but more so by the hundreds of chemicals that people are exposed to on a daily basis throughout the world, as we illustrate in our book.\n\nWill Unregulated Chemicals Continue to Compromise Fertility?\nNot only are these reproductive health changes interconnected, but they are largely driven by a common cause: the presence of endocrine disrupting chemicals (EDCs) in our world. These hormonehijacking chemicals — which include phthalates, bisphenol A, perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS), and flame retardants, among others — have become ubiquitous in our modern world. We ingest them in the air we breathe, our food and water, and the products we slather on our skin. That’s because they’re present in plastic water bottles and food packaging, nonstick cookware, electronic devices, cosmetic and personalcare products, cleaning supplies, and many other items that we use regularly.\n\nInside the human body they are playing havoc with the building blocks of sexual and reproductive development and reproductive health. These chemicals began being produced in increasing numbers after 1950, which is when sperm counts, testosterone levels, and fertility began to decline. Unbeknownst to many people, these chemicals are altering our testosterone levels, along with estrogen levels, and having detrimental effects on human reproductive health and development.\n\nMost people also don’t realize that these chemicals are largely unregulated: Unlike drugs, which must have a proven record of safety and effectiveness before they’re allowed onto the market, in the United States chemicals are presumed to be safe until they’re proven otherwise. This means that myriad chemicals that are used to manufacture an incredible array of consumer products are largely unregulated. In other words, we’ve been using each other and our unborn children as unwitting guinea pigs for EDC exposures — and this experiment is taking a toll on our reproductive health and potentially the future of the human race. \n\nShanna Swan, PhD, is one of the world’s leading environmental and reproductive epidemiologists and a professor of environmental medicine and public health at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai in New York City. She and Stacey Colino, a frequent contributor to Everyday Health, are coauthors of Count Down: How Our Modern World Is Threatening Sperm Counts, Altering Male and Female Reproductive Development, and Imperiling the Future of the Human Race, published in February 2021.</item>
        <item>Throughout the world, testosterone levels are decreasing, and most people don’t know this or understand the significance of this trend. It’s problematic on multiple levels — for reproduction, health and longevity, libido, and proper fetal development during pregnancy. While researching and writing our new book Count Down: How Our Modern World Is Threatening Sperm Counts, Altering Male and Female Reproductive Development, and Imperiling the Future of the Human Race, we discovered research showing not only that sperm counts and testosterone levels are declining, but they’re doing so in tandem and at an alarming rate of 1 percent per year in Western countries.\n\nAt first blush, this may not sound like a big deal, but it is. It adds up to more than a 10 percent decline per decade and more than a 50 percent drop over 50 years. Meanwhile, rates of testicular cancer and the prevalence of erectile dysfunction have been increasing at a similar rate, and so have miscarriage rates in the United States. It’s not a pretty picture.\n\nIts Not Just About Sperm Counts; Reproductive Health Is Also at Stake\nIt’s noteworthy that the use of testosterone replacement therapy has increased dramatically among younger men, many of whom are taking it to boost their energy and muscle mass. In fact, a study in the April 2017 issue of the Journal of Urology found that the use of testosterone replacement therapy had increased fourfold among men between the ages of 18 and 45 and threefold among older men from 2003 to 2013. What men don’t realize is that with testosterone replacement, a decline in sperm production occurs, so they’re working at crosspurposes with their best interests if they want to have children.\n\nThe Hormone Testosterone Plays a Role in Women’s Health as Well as Men’s Health\nPeople often think of testosterone as a “male” hormone, but girls and women also produce testosterone in their ovaries (in guys it’s made by the testes); however, women produce it in much smaller amounts than men do. In both sexes, the hormone affects energy levels, cognitive function, libido, and sexual function. When women’s lack of sexual desire is persistent and distressing, it’s called hypoactive sexual desire disorder, and according to a consensus statement in a 2019 issue of the NEJM Journal Watch Women’s Health, “Testosterone therapy is indicated only for postmenopausal women with hypoactive sexual desire disorder (HSDD), with evidence suggesting moderate therapeutic effects.” So clearly testosterone plays a crucial role in women’s sexual function, just as it does for men.\n\nFor women, there’s a sweet spot for testosterone levels at various stages of life. Too much or too little can send reproductive health and development in the wrong direction. For example, when a woman is pregnant, in order for her baby to develop properly, it needs to be exposed to the right amount of testosterone in the womb at the right time — it’s the Goldilocks conundrum in play.\nHere’s where things get tricky: Research has found that if a male fetus gets too little testosterone while in the womb, his genitals and his brain are likely to become less maletypical. By contrast, if a female fetus is exposed to too much testosterone in utero — perhaps because she has congenital adrenal hyperplasia, a genetic condition — her brain and genitals will be less femaletypical after she’s born. In other words, exposure to testosterone has the ability to push a developing fetus along the continuum between male and female. Once they’re born and start to grow up, these hormonal effects can influence the way children perceive themselves in terms of gender; what’s more, they can affect the kids’ activity preferences (playing with cars and trucks vs. dolls, for instance) and their style of play (roughandtumble vs. gentle, for example).\n\nIn addition, when girls and women have elevated levels of testosterone — as they do with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), which research suggests is increasing in incidence — they often have irregular periods, fertility challenges (including a higher rate of miscarriages), hair in unwanted places, acne, and excessive weight gain. And if they do have babies, these women’s baby girls are likely to have a higher body mass index (BMI), according to research published in April 2016 in Reproductive System and Sexual Disorders: Current Research.\n\nWhy Testosterone Levels Are Out of Whack\nNow that you know how testosterone levels affect women’s and men’s reproductive health, here’s the shocker: All the reproductive changes that have been occurring in recent years are too synchronous to be a coincidence. These changes are partly driven by poor lifestyle choices (such as smoking, binge drinking, and the like) but more so by the hundreds of chemicals that people are exposed to on a daily basis throughout the world, as we illustrate in our book.\n\nWill Unregulated Chemicals Continue to Compromise Fertility?\nNot only are these reproductive health changes interconnected, but they are largely driven by a common cause: the presence of endocrine disrupting chemicals (EDCs) in our world. These hormonehijacking chemicals — which include phthalates, bisphenol A, perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS), and flame retardants, among others — have become ubiquitous in our modern world. We ingest them in the air we breathe, our food and water, and the products we slather on our skin. That’s because they’re present in plastic water bottles and food packaging, nonstick cookware, electronic devices, cosmetic and personalcare products, cleaning supplies, and many other items that we use regularly.\n\nInside the human body they are playing havoc with the building blocks of sexual and reproductive development and reproductive health. These chemicals began being produced in increasing numbers after 1950, which is when sperm counts, testosterone levels, and fertility began to decline. Unbeknownst to many people, these chemicals are altering our testosterone levels, along with estrogen levels, and having detrimental effects on human reproductive health and development.\n\nMost people also don’t realize that these chemicals are largely unregulated: Unlike drugs, which must have a proven record of safety and effectiveness before they’re allowed onto the market, in the United States chemicals are presumed to be safe until they’re proven otherwise. This means that myriad chemicals that are used to manufacture an incredible array of consumer products are largely unregulated. In other words, we’ve been using each other and our unborn children as unwitting guinea pigs for EDC exposures — and this experiment is taking a toll on our reproductive health and potentially the future of the human race. \n\nShanna Swan, PhD, is one of the world’s leading environmental and reproductive epidemiologists and a professor of environmental medicine and public health at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai in New York City. She and Stacey Colino, a frequent contributor to Everyday Health, are coauthors of Count Down: How Our Modern World Is Threatening Sperm Counts, Altering Male and Female Reproductive Development, and Imperiling the Future of the Human Race, published in February 2021.</item>
        <item>Bacterial vaginosis (BV) is a common infection caused by a change in the bacterial balance in the vagina — and a treatable problem many women suffer from frequently. Now, a new study published in August 2020 in Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology suggests that her male partner may play a role in this.\n\nWhen the Penis Microbiome and the Vaginal Microbiome Meet\nResearchers followed 168 heterosexual couples in which the women did not have bacterial vaginosis at the start of the study and assessed the presence of BV after one month, six months, and a year, using vaginal swabs; also, at each visit, the men had swabs taken of the bacteria in and around their penises (what’s called the “penile microbiome”). Over the course of the year, 31 percent of the women developed BV. The incidence was slightly higher among women whose partners hadn’t been circumcised, perhaps because the warm, moist space under the foreskin can harbor bacteria and allow them to grow. \n\nThe Penile Microbiome and its Role in Women’s BV\nWhen the researchers considered the results of the men’s swabs along with the women’s, they found that the composition of a man’s penile microbiome — namely, the presence of certain bacteria — could predict the development of BV in their female partners. “Bacteria that have been associated with BV in women have been recovered from the skin of the penis, the semen, and men’s urine,” explains study lead author Supriya Mehta, PhD, an associate professor of epidemiology and biostatistics at the University of Illinois Chicago School of Public Health. “Like many other bacteria, the exchange of penile and vaginal bacteria is most likely bidirectional.”\n\nSharing Microbes During Intimate Encounters\nSimply put, a man’s penis has a microbiome, just as a woman’s vagina does, and during penetrative sex these communities of bacteria can interact with each other and impact each partner’s reproductive health. It may be that BVassociated bacteria from some men’s microbiomes can directly impact the onset of BV in women when they’re transmitted to the vagina during intercourse or that the penile bacteria may disrupt the natural balance of vaginal bacteria in ways that could induce BV over time. More research needs to be done to tease out the exact mechanisms but this much is clear: BV is a hisandhers proposition. \n\nBacterial Vaginosis: Causes and Risk Factors\nIndeed, the study findings may be a game changer in terms of understanding the possible causes of BV and perhaps the best ways to treat it. “Prior thought has been that the alkalinity of semen in the vagina produced this alteration in vaginal flora [that could lead to BV],” notes Michael Cackovic, MD, an obgyn at The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center in Columbus. “What this study suggests is that the penile microbiome may be a cause of the disruption of the vaginal environment.”\n\nBV Can Be Treated; Problems May Occur When It Is Not\nThis new understanding is especially important because if left untreated BV can lead to pregnancy complications (such as having a lowbirthweight baby or premature rupture of the membranes), as well as increasing a woman’s susceptibility to sexually transmitted diseases such as HIV, herpes, gonorrhea, and chlamydia.\n\nBacterial Vaginosis Cases Tend to Come Back Often\nWhat’s more, BV has a high rate of recurrence — up to 58 percent of women have a recurrence over the course of a year after being treated with oral antibiotics, research published in the Journal of Infectious Disease found. (Symptoms of BV can include a white or gray vaginal mucus or discharge with a strong fishy odor and sometimes itching, according to the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists.)\n\n“I would use this study to counsel those patients [who are] frustrated by recurrent bacterial vaginosis that this may be another reason causing the recurrence,” Dr. Cackovic says. \n\nWould Treating a Woman’s Male Sex Partner Help Prevent BV? \nIn fact, the study findings suggest that treating BV in both partners may be more effective in reducing recurrence rates than just treating the women. “Our next step is to design a randomized controlled trial to treat male sex partners with antibiotics to see if this can reduce BV recurrence in female sex partners,” Dr. Mehta says. “We need to find out what amount, duration, and type of antibiotics are most effective, and if men are willing to take the medicine when they themselves do not have symptoms.”\n\nInclusion of Sex Partners and Holistic Healthcare\nAnother important takehome message, Mehta adds: “I would like for clinicians, researchers, and the public to be inclusive of male sex partners in their efforts to improve women’s reproductive health.”</item>
        <item>Bacterial vaginosis (BV) is a common infection caused by a change in the bacterial balance in the vagina — and a treatable problem many women suffer from frequently. Now, a new study published in August 2020 in Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology suggests that her male partner may play a role in this.\n\nWhen the Penis Microbiome and the Vaginal Microbiome Meet\nResearchers followed 168 heterosexual couples in which the women did not have bacterial vaginosis at the start of the study and assessed the presence of BV after one month, six months, and a year, using vaginal swabs; also, at each visit, the men had swabs taken of the bacteria in and around their penises (what’s called the “penile microbiome”). Over the course of the year, 31 percent of the women developed BV. The incidence was slightly higher among women whose partners hadn’t been circumcised, perhaps because the warm, moist space under the foreskin can harbor bacteria and allow them to grow. \n\nThe Penile Microbiome and its Role in Women’s BV\nWhen the researchers considered the results of the men’s swabs along with the women’s, they found that the composition of a man’s penile microbiome — namely, the presence of certain bacteria — could predict the development of BV in their female partners. “Bacteria that have been associated with BV in women have been recovered from the skin of the penis, the semen, and men’s urine,” explains study lead author Supriya Mehta, PhD, an associate professor of epidemiology and biostatistics at the University of Illinois Chicago School of Public Health. “Like many other bacteria, the exchange of penile and vaginal bacteria is most likely bidirectional.”\n\nSharing Microbes During Intimate Encounters\nSimply put, a man’s penis has a microbiome, just as a woman’s vagina does, and during penetrative sex these communities of bacteria can interact with each other and impact each partner’s reproductive health. It may be that BVassociated bacteria from some men’s microbiomes can directly impact the onset of BV in women when they’re transmitted to the vagina during intercourse or that the penile bacteria may disrupt the natural balance of vaginal bacteria in ways that could induce BV over time. More research needs to be done to tease out the exact mechanisms but this much is clear: BV is a hisandhers proposition. \n\nBacterial Vaginosis: Causes and Risk Factors\nIndeed, the study findings may be a game changer in terms of understanding the possible causes of BV and perhaps the best ways to treat it. “Prior thought has been that the alkalinity of semen in the vagina produced this alteration in vaginal flora [that could lead to BV],” notes Michael Cackovic, MD, an obgyn at The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center in Columbus. “What this study suggests is that the penile microbiome may be a cause of the disruption of the vaginal environment.”\n\nBV Can Be Treated; Problems May Occur When It Is Not\nThis new understanding is especially important because if left untreated BV can lead to pregnancy complications (such as having a lowbirthweight baby or premature rupture of the membranes), as well as increasing a woman’s susceptibility to sexually transmitted diseases such as HIV, herpes, gonorrhea, and chlamydia.\n\nBacterial Vaginosis Cases Tend to Come Back Often\nWhat’s more, BV has a high rate of recurrence — up to 58 percent of women have a recurrence over the course of a year after being treated with oral antibiotics, research published in the Journal of Infectious Disease found. (Symptoms of BV can include a white or gray vaginal mucus or discharge with a strong fishy odor and sometimes itching, according to the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists.)\n\n“I would use this study to counsel those patients [who are] frustrated by recurrent bacterial vaginosis that this may be another reason causing the recurrence,” Dr. Cackovic says. \n\nWould Treating a Woman’s Male Sex Partner Help Prevent BV? \nIn fact, the study findings suggest that treating BV in both partners may be more effective in reducing recurrence rates than just treating the women. “Our next step is to design a randomized controlled trial to treat male sex partners with antibiotics to see if this can reduce BV recurrence in female sex partners,” Dr. Mehta says. “We need to find out what amount, duration, and type of antibiotics are most effective, and if men are willing to take the medicine when they themselves do not have symptoms.”\n\nInclusion of Sex Partners and Holistic Healthcare\nAnother important takehome message, Mehta adds: “I would like for clinicians, researchers, and the public to be inclusive of male sex partners in their efforts to improve women’s reproductive health.”</item>
        <item>When it comes to planning pregnancy, preconception counseling on diet and exercise is almost exclusively directed at the woman. A new study that included almost one million pregnancies suggests that way of thinking may be outdated, and perhaps men need to be in on those prepregnancy healthy lifestyle discussions, too.\n\nA Man’s Health Matters When It Comes to Pregnancy Outcome\n\nA retrospective study that looked at pregnancies between 2009 and 2016 published December 18, 2020, in Human Reproduction found that if a fathertobe has three or more medical conditions that are part of metabolic syndrome: obesity, diabetes, high blood pressure, or high cholesterol, the risk for losing a pregnancy was 27 percent compared with 10 percent for men who had no medical conditions\n\nThere’s a Link Between Paternal Health and Pregnancy Loss\n“Preconception counseling, things like prenatal vitamins and living a healthy lifestyle, has only focused on women. This is the first study to show an association between the preconception paternal health and pregnancy loss,” says Michael Eisenberg, MD, associate professor of urology at Stanford University School of Medicine in Palo Alto, California, and lead author of the study\n\nThe More Conditions of Metabolic Syndrome DadtoBe Has, the Higher the Risk for Pregnancy Loss\nEisenberg and his team analyzed data from U.S. insurance claims that covered 958,804 pregnancies between the years 2009 and 2016. Researchers evaluated the health of the father according to records of medical conditions, which included components of metabolic syndrome (obesity, diabetes, high blood pressure, and high cholesterol) as well as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), depression, and heart disease.\nThe burden of chronic disease for all the men was calculated by reviewing their health history of heart failure, heart attack, diseases of the blood vessels, kidney and liver disease, cancer, stroke, and dementia.\n\nCalculations were adjusted to account for other factors that can impact pregnancy, including the mother’s age, health, weight, and whether either parent was a smoker.\n\nA total of 4.6 men in the study were over 45 years old and 23.3 had at least one component of metabolic syndrome prior to conception. Of the pregnancies included, there were 785,809 live births and 172,995 pregnancies lost to ectopic pregnancy, miscarriage, or stillbirth. \n\nInvestigators found that the more components of metabolic syndrome the father had, the higher the risk for a pregnancy loss.\n\nThe risk of pregnancy loss was:\n\n17 percent when the father had no components of metabolic syndrome\n21 percent when the father had one metabolic syndrome component\n23 percent where there were two components\n27 percent if the father had three or more components\n\n“The fact that the risk of an adverse event in pregnancy increased with each additional health component strengthens the findings of this study,” says Chad Aaron Grotegut, MD, professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the Wake Forest School of Medicine and a maternalfetal medicine specialist at Wake Forest Baptist Health, both in WinstonSalem, North Carolina. Dr. Grotegut was not involved in this research. “I think that seeing that sort of dose response strengthens the argument that this may be a true finding,” he says.\n\nAge of Parents Impacts Pregnancy Loss Risk, Too\nInvestigators also discovered that the risk of pregnancy losses increased with the mother’s age and the number of medical conditions she had, but even after allowing for that, the association between the health of the father and pregnancy losses remained. The risk of losing a pregnancy also went up as the age of the father increased.\n\nThe authors do a good job of acknowledging there are some limitations to the study, says Grotegut. “In research, anytime that you’re going back and analyzing data that was collected for a different purpose, there’s always a concern that certain data or conditions were either not recorded or not recorded correctly,” he says.\n\nPopulation for this Study Was Not Inclusive\n\nOther limitations are that the data included only people who were privately insured and employed, and the data didn’t include race, substance abuse, or sociodemographic status such as education level or income, said the authors.\n\nWhat Is It About Men’s Health That Could Impact Pregnancy Risk?\nAlthough this study wasn’t designed to uncover the “why” behind the association between paternal health and the risk of pregnancy loss, there is existing research that offers a few clues. “There have been some studies to suggest that the sperm in men that are older, who smoke or who have obesity may have abnormal epigenetic signatures in their sperm,” says Eisenberg.\n\nEpigenetics is the study of how your behaviors and environment can cause changes that impact the way your genes function, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Epigenetic changes are reversible and do not change your DNA sequence, but they can affect how your body reads a DNA sequence.\n\nThese epigenetic changes don’t change the DNA code, but they change how well and how efficiently that DNA is expressed, he explains.\n\nIt’s possible that these chronic health conditions of the men lead to poor epigenetic signatures of the sperm, says Eisenberg. “If the sperm DNA can’t be expressed efficiently or perfectly, that may lead to a poor embryo or a poor placenta that then can lead to this adverse pregnancy trajectory where it’s more likely to end,” he says.\n\nResearch has shown that a pregnant woman’s environment and behavior during pregnancy, for example whether or not she eats a healthy diet, can change the baby’s epigenetics, according to the CDC.\n\nPaternal Age Linked to Increased Risks at Birth\nEisenberg and his colleagues published a 2018 study in The BMJ that used data from 40.5 million live births from a U.S. national datasharing program to examine the impact, if any, of the father’s age.\n\nAfter controlling for factors such as education level, marital status, smoking history, access to healthcare and the mother’s age, investigators found that older fathers were linked to increased risks at birth, including low birth weight and seizures. The infants born to older fathers were more likely to require ventilation and neonatal intensive care as well.\n\nFathers May Play a Role in Determining the Health of the Placenta, Animal Research Suggests\n\nAlthough there aren’t any human studies to date, a study published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences looked at mules, which have horse mothers and donkey fathers, and hinnies, which have horse fathers and donkey mothers. Investigators found that genes from the animals’ fathers were predominant in the placenta.\n\nThe placenta is the organ that gives the fetus nourishment and oxygen and filters out waste products through the umbilical cord.\n\nFurther Research Needed to Strengthen the Association Between Paternal Health and Pregnancy Problems\n\nOne avenue for further research would drill down deeper to examine the individual health of the fatherstobe, says Eisenberg. “For example, if a person has diabetes, let’s look at how tightly they’re controlling their blood sugars and how they are doing it, whether that be through diet and exercise or medication. We could discover that what we’re seeing as far as increased risk in pregnancy could be the disease itself, but it could also be the treatment for the disease,” he says.\n\nReplicating the study and looking at individuals with more detail is really crucial to understanding what is going on, adds Eisenberg.\n\nHealth Advice for Prospective Fathers, Families\n\nThis is only one study, and at this point it hasn’t been proved that the father’s health causes the increased risk in pregnancy, says Eisenberg. That being said, the advice that we would give a man would not be harmful, even if further studies don’t prove causation, he says.\n\nMen should be mindful of their diet, to exercise, maintain a healthy body weight, and check in with their primary care doctor to make sure that they’re in good health, says Eisenberg. “I think that’s reasonable, it’s going to benefit their health, and this data suggests that it would hopefully benefit the pregnancy as well,” he says. “Maybe this could be an extra carrot to get people, specifically men, to adhere to some of those recommendations,” he adds.</item>
        <item>When it comes to planning pregnancy, preconception counseling on diet and exercise is almost exclusively directed at the woman. A new study that included almost one million pregnancies suggests that way of thinking may be outdated, and perhaps men need to be in on those prepregnancy healthy lifestyle discussions, too.\n\nA Man’s Health Matters When It Comes to Pregnancy Outcome\n\nA retrospective study that looked at pregnancies between 2009 and 2016 published December 18, 2020, in Human Reproduction found that if a fathertobe has three or more medical conditions that are part of metabolic syndrome: obesity, diabetes, high blood pressure, or high cholesterol, the risk for losing a pregnancy was 27 percent compared with 10 percent for men who had no medical conditions\n\nThere’s a Link Between Paternal Health and Pregnancy Loss\n“Preconception counseling, things like prenatal vitamins and living a healthy lifestyle, has only focused on women. This is the first study to show an association between the preconception paternal health and pregnancy loss,” says Michael Eisenberg, MD, associate professor of urology at Stanford University School of Medicine in Palo Alto, California, and lead author of the study\n\nThe More Conditions of Metabolic Syndrome DadtoBe Has, the Higher the Risk for Pregnancy Loss\nEisenberg and his team analyzed data from U.S. insurance claims that covered 958,804 pregnancies between the years 2009 and 2016. Researchers evaluated the health of the father according to records of medical conditions, which included components of metabolic syndrome (obesity, diabetes, high blood pressure, and high cholesterol) as well as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), depression, and heart disease.\nThe burden of chronic disease for all the men was calculated by reviewing their health history of heart failure, heart attack, diseases of the blood vessels, kidney and liver disease, cancer, stroke, and dementia.\n\nCalculations were adjusted to account for other factors that can impact pregnancy, including the mother’s age, health, weight, and whether either parent was a smoker.\n\nA total of 4.6 men in the study were over 45 years old and 23.3 had at least one component of metabolic syndrome prior to conception. Of the pregnancies included, there were 785,809 live births and 172,995 pregnancies lost to ectopic pregnancy, miscarriage, or stillbirth. \n\nInvestigators found that the more components of metabolic syndrome the father had, the higher the risk for a pregnancy loss.\n\nThe risk of pregnancy loss was:\n\n17 percent when the father had no components of metabolic syndrome\n21 percent when the father had one metabolic syndrome component\n23 percent where there were two components\n27 percent if the father had three or more components\n\n“The fact that the risk of an adverse event in pregnancy increased with each additional health component strengthens the findings of this study,” says Chad Aaron Grotegut, MD, professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the Wake Forest School of Medicine and a maternalfetal medicine specialist at Wake Forest Baptist Health, both in WinstonSalem, North Carolina. Dr. Grotegut was not involved in this research. “I think that seeing that sort of dose response strengthens the argument that this may be a true finding,” he says.\n\nAge of Parents Impacts Pregnancy Loss Risk, Too\nInvestigators also discovered that the risk of pregnancy losses increased with the mother’s age and the number of medical conditions she had, but even after allowing for that, the association between the health of the father and pregnancy losses remained. The risk of losing a pregnancy also went up as the age of the father increased.\n\nThe authors do a good job of acknowledging there are some limitations to the study, says Grotegut. “In research, anytime that you’re going back and analyzing data that was collected for a different purpose, there’s always a concern that certain data or conditions were either not recorded or not recorded correctly,” he says.\n\nPopulation for this Study Was Not Inclusive\n\nOther limitations are that the data included only people who were privately insured and employed, and the data didn’t include race, substance abuse, or sociodemographic status such as education level or income, said the authors.\n\nWhat Is It About Men’s Health That Could Impact Pregnancy Risk?\nAlthough this study wasn’t designed to uncover the “why” behind the association between paternal health and the risk of pregnancy loss, there is existing research that offers a few clues. “There have been some studies to suggest that the sperm in men that are older, who smoke or who have obesity may have abnormal epigenetic signatures in their sperm,” says Eisenberg.\n\nEpigenetics is the study of how your behaviors and environment can cause changes that impact the way your genes function, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Epigenetic changes are reversible and do not change your DNA sequence, but they can affect how your body reads a DNA sequence.\n\nThese epigenetic changes don’t change the DNA code, but they change how well and how efficiently that DNA is expressed, he explains.\n\nIt’s possible that these chronic health conditions of the men lead to poor epigenetic signatures of the sperm, says Eisenberg. “If the sperm DNA can’t be expressed efficiently or perfectly, that may lead to a poor embryo or a poor placenta that then can lead to this adverse pregnancy trajectory where it’s more likely to end,” he says.\n\nResearch has shown that a pregnant woman’s environment and behavior during pregnancy, for example whether or not she eats a healthy diet, can change the baby’s epigenetics, according to the CDC.\n\nPaternal Age Linked to Increased Risks at Birth\nEisenberg and his colleagues published a 2018 study in The BMJ that used data from 40.5 million live births from a U.S. national datasharing program to examine the impact, if any, of the father’s age.\n\nAfter controlling for factors such as education level, marital status, smoking history, access to healthcare and the mother’s age, investigators found that older fathers were linked to increased risks at birth, including low birth weight and seizures. The infants born to older fathers were more likely to require ventilation and neonatal intensive care as well.\n\nFathers May Play a Role in Determining the Health of the Placenta, Animal Research Suggests\n\nAlthough there aren’t any human studies to date, a study published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences looked at mules, which have horse mothers and donkey fathers, and hinnies, which have horse fathers and donkey mothers. Investigators found that genes from the animals’ fathers were predominant in the placenta.\n\nThe placenta is the organ that gives the fetus nourishment and oxygen and filters out waste products through the umbilical cord.\n\nFurther Research Needed to Strengthen the Association Between Paternal Health and Pregnancy Problems\n\nOne avenue for further research would drill down deeper to examine the individual health of the fatherstobe, says Eisenberg. “For example, if a person has diabetes, let’s look at how tightly they’re controlling their blood sugars and how they are doing it, whether that be through diet and exercise or medication. We could discover that what we’re seeing as far as increased risk in pregnancy could be the disease itself, but it could also be the treatment for the disease,” he says.\n\nReplicating the study and looking at individuals with more detail is really crucial to understanding what is going on, adds Eisenberg.\n\nHealth Advice for Prospective Fathers, Families\n\nThis is only one study, and at this point it hasn’t been proved that the father’s health causes the increased risk in pregnancy, says Eisenberg. That being said, the advice that we would give a man would not be harmful, even if further studies don’t prove causation, he says.\n\nMen should be mindful of their diet, to exercise, maintain a healthy body weight, and check in with their primary care doctor to make sure that they’re in good health, says Eisenberg. “I think that’s reasonable, it’s going to benefit their health, and this data suggests that it would hopefully benefit the pregnancy as well,” he says. “Maybe this could be an extra carrot to get people, specifically men, to adhere to some of those recommendations,” he adds.</item>
        <item>Bacterial vaginosis (BV) is a common infection caused by a change in the bacterial balance in the vagina — and a treatable problem many women suffer from frequently. Now, a new study published in August 2020 in Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology suggests that her male partner may play a role in this.\n\nWhen the Penis Microbiome and the Vaginal Microbiome Meet\nResearchers followed 168 heterosexual couples in which the women did not have bacterial vaginosis at the start of the study and assessed the presence of BV after one month, six months, and a year, using vaginal swabs; also, at each visit, the men had swabs taken of the bacteria in and around their penises (what’s called the “penile microbiome”). Over the course of the year, 31 percent of the women developed BV. The incidence was slightly higher among women whose partners hadn’t been circumcised, perhaps because the warm, moist space under the foreskin can harbor bacteria and allow them to grow. \n\nThe Penile Microbiome and its Role in Women’s BV\nWhen the researchers considered the results of the men’s swabs along with the women’s, they found that the composition of a man’s penile microbiome — namely, the presence of certain bacteria — could predict the development of BV in their female partners. “Bacteria that have been associated with BV in women have been recovered from the skin of the penis, the semen, and men’s urine,” explains study lead author Supriya Mehta, PhD, an associate professor of epidemiology and biostatistics at the University of Illinois Chicago School of Public Health. “Like many other bacteria, the exchange of penile and vaginal bacteria is most likely bidirectional.”\n\nSharing Microbes During Intimate Encounters\nSimply put, a man’s penis has a microbiome, just as a woman’s vagina does, and during penetrative sex these communities of bacteria can interact with each other and impact each partner’s reproductive health. It may be that BVassociated bacteria from some men’s microbiomes can directly impact the onset of BV in women when they’re transmitted to the vagina during intercourse or that the penile bacteria may disrupt the natural balance of vaginal bacteria in ways that could induce BV over time. More research needs to be done to tease out the exact mechanisms but this much is clear: BV is a hisandhers proposition. \n\nBacterial Vaginosis: Causes and Risk Factors\nIndeed, the study findings may be a game changer in terms of understanding the possible causes of BV and perhaps the best ways to treat it. “Prior thought has been that the alkalinity of semen in the vagina produced this alteration in vaginal flora [that could lead to BV],” notes Michael Cackovic, MD, an obgyn at The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center in Columbus. “What this study suggests is that the penile microbiome may be a cause of the disruption of the vaginal environment.”\n\nBV Can Be Treated; Problems May Occur When It Is Not\nThis new understanding is especially important because if left untreated BV can lead to pregnancy complications (such as having a lowbirthweight baby or premature rupture of the membranes), as well as increasing a woman’s susceptibility to sexually transmitted diseases such as HIV, herpes, gonorrhea, and chlamydia.\n\nBacterial Vaginosis Cases Tend to Come Back Often\nWhat’s more, BV has a high rate of recurrence — up to 58 percent of women have a recurrence over the course of a year after being treated with oral antibiotics, research published in the Journal of Infectious Disease found. (Symptoms of BV can include a white or gray vaginal mucus or discharge with a strong fishy odor and sometimes itching, according to the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists.)\n\n“I would use this study to counsel those patients [who are] frustrated by recurrent bacterial vaginosis that this may be another reason causing the recurrence,” Dr. Cackovic says. \n\nWould Treating a Woman’s Male Sex Partner Help Prevent BV? \nIn fact, the study findings suggest that treating BV in both partners may be more effective in reducing recurrence rates than just treating the women. “Our next step is to design a randomized controlled trial to treat male sex partners with antibiotics to see if this can reduce BV recurrence in female sex partners,” Dr. Mehta says. “We need to find out what amount, duration, and type of antibiotics are most effective, and if men are willing to take the medicine when they themselves do not have symptoms.”\n\nInclusion of Sex Partners and Holistic Healthcare\nAnother important takehome message, Mehta adds: “I would like for clinicians, researchers, and the public to be inclusive of male sex partners in their efforts to improve women’s reproductive health.”</item>
        <item>Let’s talk about sex. Sexual health is an essential part of overall emotional and physical wellbeing. But if you’re experiencing a sexual problem, the last thing you probably want to do is talk about it. If shame is keeping you from seeking help, know this: 43 percent of women and 31 percent of men report some degree of sexual dysfunction. Sex therapy is designed to get to the bottom of sexual issues and reverse them.\n\nWorking With a Therapist to Address Libido Problems and Other Sexual Health Issues\n\nWhether you work with a psychiatrist, psychologist, or marriage or sex counselor, sex therapy can help with a variety of physical and emotional issues that can interfere with sexual satisfaction, such as erectile dysfunction, low libido, a history of abuse, and others. And it can help you and your partner work through these issues in a supportive and educational environment.\n\nSo what does sex therapy really entail? And who qualifies as a sex therapist? Read on to discover the truth about this type of therapy.\n\nWhat Is Sex Therapy and How Can It Help?\n\nContrary to what some believe, there’s nothing strange, deviant, or kinky going on behind the door to a sex therapist’s office. Indeed, sex therapy is not very different from other forms of psychological counseling. “Sex therapy is a type of psychotherapy that also takes into account possible physical problems. When a couple comes in with a sexual problem, we try to figure out how each of them could be contributing to the issue. We examine behavior, gradually interpret that for them, and come up with solutions,” says Barbara Bartlik, MD, a psychiatrist and sex therapist at Weill Cornell Medicine in New York City.\n\nWhat Happens in a Sex Therapy Session?\nYour therapist will help you work through emotional issues that may be contributing to sexual issues, such as erectile dysfunction, according to Drogo Montague, MD, a urologist at the Cleveland Clinic in Ohio. If performance anxiety is an issue, sex therapy would typically begin with learning about performance anxiety, then move on to teaching a couple how to establish open lines of communication to discuss sexual wants and needs, Dr. Montague explains. The couple may also explore issues causing relationship stress, he adds.\n\nWhen May Sex Therapy Be Recommended?\nSex therapy may be recommended in a variety of scenarios, says Michael Krychman, MD, executive director of the Southern California Center for Sexual Health and Survivorship Medicine in Newport Beach and coauthor of The Sexual Spark. Here are some of the most common scenarios:\nPersonal Conflict Issues Related to Sexuality This includes, for example, sexual trauma or assault. Dr. Krychman recommends seeking individual therapy first to cope with these issues, then gradually including your partner as needed.\n\nConflict About the Relationship A common example here would be a partner experiencing sexual boredom. In this case, it’s better to seek therapy alone first so that you can better understand yourself and your own sexual concerns, then incorporate your partner, says Krychman.\n\nCompulsive Sexual Behavior (CSB) Once again, in this scenario it’s better for the person with the compulsive behavior or the partner to see a therapist alone first, then bring in the partner. “Sometimes, personal emotions of betrayal, guilt, or fear may need to be explored before incorporating your partner,” explains Krychman. “The one suffering from CSB may also experience a wide range of emotions, such as fear, shame, and anxiety. Addressing your personal emotional experience is important prior to bringing and dealing with your partner — this may enhance communication.”\n\nCouple, Marital, and Sexual Problems For instance, with the infidelity of one partner, Krychman typically recommends that the couple tackle the concern or problem together from the start and address the roles they may have played with respect to the issue. “No one is blameless in a dysfunctional relationship, and couples can jointly work together to improve the quality of their experience,” he says.\n\nPersonal Coping Difficulties Related to Sexuality This area might include if you’ve just been diagnosed with a sexually transmitted infection and want to learn how to disclose your status to your partner or partners.\n\nYou’ll Learn to Be Mindful and More Aware\nIn mindfulness training, you learn to be present and focused on the here and now, rather than letting yourself get distracted by grocery lists and carpool plans. When using this concept in sex therapy, you learn to block out extraneous thoughts as well as negative thoughts you might have about your body or your performance. Instead, you are guided in thinking only about how your body is reacting to sexual stimulation.</item>
        <item>In the best of times, sex can be complicated, but in a pandemic, even more so. With mandatory social distancing and mask wearing, accompanied by excessive hand washing, acts of intimacy come with their own set of new rules, too.\n\nExperts have learned a lot about COVID–19 since stay–athome orders first hit the United States last spring. During that time, health officials in New York City, Washington DC, and elsewhere released guidelines on how to have safe sex during the pandemic. \n\nAlthough widespread vaccination is under way, these new guidelines regarding safe sex are unlikely to go away anytime soon, since no one actually knows when the pandemic will officially come to an end. As experts continue to learn more about the novel coronavirus and its variants, the advice they give may change. Here’s what experts want you to know about safe sex and the pandemic right now.\n\nHow to Practice Safe Sex During the Pandemic \nAccording to Dr. Flowers, an important part of having sex during the pandemic is making sure you and your partners are on the same page, just as you would while forming a COVID pod. \n\n“Making sure people are adhering to the same practices is important,” says Flowers. “There are questions we can ask folks around the way they have been distancing and making sure you have a shared value system around what safe distancing looks like.”\n\nCan COVID19 Be Transmitted Through Body Fluids During Sex?\nThe main risk factor is that COVID19 is highly contagious through the saliva and mucus of an infected person, and sex traditionally requires people to be within six feet of each other. Being in the same room as an infected person significantly increases the likelihood that the virus will jump from one person to another, even without touching each other, especially if one person is carrying a mutated form of the virus. \n\nIn addition, a study published in May 2020 in the journal Gastroenterology determined that the virus is detectable in fecal matter, in some cases even when respiratory tests were negative, and can be transmitted to an uninfected person through the mouth. A more recent small retrospective study, published in January 2021 in the Journal of Medical Virology, found that in people who had severe cases of COVID19, viral RNA could be detected in the fecal matter of some up to 46 days after they were exposed to the virus. Depending on your beneaththesheets habits, this could be an issue. \n\nA study published July 2020 in the journal Clinical Infectious Diseases found that the coronavirus does not appear to be present in vaginal fluid and several studies have found no presence of the virus in semen of recovered people. However, a study published May 2020 in JAMA Network Open found that SARSCoV2 can be present in the semen of patients with COVID19 and while recovering. \n\nWho’s a Safe Sex Partner During the Pandemic?\n“As with sexually transmitted infections, sex with a new partner always brings with it some amount of risk. The best we can do in such circumstances is to assess this risk honestly and make an informed decision,” says Kumi Smith, PhD, an assistant professor of epidemiology and community health at the University of Minnesota School of Public Health in Minneapolis.\n\n“Practically speaking, though, a partner with whom you live or with whom you have been coisolating is probably the safest person to have sex with for the time being,” says Dr. Kumi Smith, as long as these people do not have symptoms of COVID19.\n\nAs for people who do not work from home, Kumi Smith says that it’s difficult to provide blanket guidelines, since different people who work outside the home are exposed to different levels of risk. If you or your partner is worried that they may have been exposed to COVID19, it’s a good idea to keep your distance as much as possible for the following two weeks until you can be sure they do not develop symptoms.\n\nYou Are Your Own Safest Sex Partner\nEspecially for people isolating without a partner, this is a great time to explore selfstimulation and gain a better understanding of what your body likes, Chavez says.\n\n“If you’ve never used a device before, now is a great time to try one,” says Chavez, who says to think of vibrators for masturbation as you would gym equipment for your workout.\n\nVibrators, Sex Toys, and More Useful Tools \n“Vibrators add so much variation,” she says. In fact, sex toy sales, especially vibrators, skyrocketed during stayathome orders, according to a report published in April 2020 in AdWeek. Make sure you wash and disinfect any toys or electronics that you use during your session. Not only can COVID19 live on surfaces for hours or even days, you also run the risk of spreading bacteria and fungi to your intimate parts.\n\nFlowers also recommends taking this time to brush up on fertility and sex education, especially since less than half of the states in the United States require sex education in schools, according to Planned Parenthood. Flowers recommends Afrosexology, Sex Positive Families, and Dr. Lexx the Sex Doc for people seeking credible online resources for sex education or reeducation.\n\nEmergency Contraception and Treatment Availability\nWhat do closed clinics mean for access to emergency contraception? People who are having sex may also want to be aware of how access to abortion may have changed in their state. In July, a judge in Maryland lifted the requirements during the pandemic, allowing doctors to prescribe abortion medication via telehealth without seeing patients in person. But on January 11, 2021, the U.S. Supreme Court reversed a ruling that temporarily legalized mailorder and telemedicine abortions during the pandemic, requiring women to be seen inperson to receive abortion medication.\n\nDuring normal times, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) requires women to receive medication used for abortion in person at a doctor’s office, but this regulation was temporarily reversed in July. However, the new administration has plans to reverse many of the current access barriers, including cost, related to abortion. So, these regulations may change again during the pandemic. \n\nIf you find yourself pregnant during the pandemic, do not delay getting prenatal care. Getting prenatal care early on is crucial for the baby’s health and decreases your risk of a preterm birth, according to the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.\n\nDomestic and Sexual Abuse Resources During the COVID19 Pandemic\nThe same rules as before concerning consent and abuse apply to sex during quarantine. Forcing someone to perform a sexual act is never permissible and is abuse, just as physical and emotional abuse are.\n\n“Any relationship that is abusive is dangerous and unhealthy but particularly in these times, when people may have to selfisolate with their abusive partner,” says Levkoff.\n\nAccording to Levkoff, domestic violence hotlines are seeing a significant rise in calls, and while shelters and resources are available, COVID19 has made already complicated physical and emotional safety plans more challenging.\n\nSafe Horizon, the largest victim services nonprofit organization in the United States, is offering selfquarantine options in their shelters for people who have COVID19 symptoms and who have to or choose to leave their homes. Advocates at the National Domestic Violence Hotline are available 24 hours a day at 8007997233. You can also get help through the Rape, Abuse, and Incest National Network at 8006564673</item>
        <item>Prenatal care is an important strategy for maintaining a healthy pregnancy and ensuring the best outcomes for a healthy baby. Screening is a routine part of this care; during the first trimester, it includes blood tests to detect chromosomal disorders such as Down syndrome and ultrasound to track the fetus’ growth and verify the approximate due date. Ultrasound imaging is also one of the most common ways that adnexal masses, growths that form on the organs and connective tissues around the ovaries, are discovered, according to the National Cancer Institute (NIH).\n\nAlthough adnexal masses are relatively common in pregnancy, 95 to 99 percent are benign (noncancerous) and disappear on their own, according to a study published November 2019 in the Journal of Ovarian Cancer Research. In fact, ovarian cancer is “exceedingly rare” during pregnancy (occurring in less than 1 percent), according to new research published in June 2020 by F1OOO Research. Still, both the discovery of a mass and a possible suspicion of cancer can be scary for expectant parents.\n\nWhat does it mean for the fetus’ health? Can the pregnancy be continued? And if you’ve had ovarian cancer previously, are you still able to become pregnant? Here’s what you need to know.\n\nKnow Your Ovarian Cancer Risk Most ovarian cancers actually start in the fallopian tubes, which serve as pathways to the uterus. Roughly 90 percent are epithelial, meaning that they originate in the cells residing on the outer lining of the ovaries. Ovarian cancers are characterized as benign, borderline (have low malignant potential), or malignant (cancerous), according to the American Cancer Society. \n\nFor women without a family history of ovarian cancer, risk increases with age, and more specifically, after menopause. The average age of most ovarian cancers is about 60, says Heidi Gray, MD, associate professor of gynecologic oncology at the University of Washington in Seattle.\n\nBut pregnancy in and of itself is not a risk factor, she says. In fact, previously carrying children to term before age 35 may offer extra protection against ovarian cancer, as does the use of oral contraceptives or breastfeeding, per the American Cancer Society. Most importantly, ovarian cancer during pregnancy is not commonly associated with a poorer prognosis, according to the International Network on Cancers infertility and pregnancy consensus guidelines, published October 2019 in the Annals of Oncology.\n\nA strong family history of ovarian cancer (or breast or colorectal cancer) increases overall ovarian cancer risk and increases the likelihood for harboring a pathogenic genetic mutation like BRCA1, or BRCA2, especially if a relative (especially mother, sister, or aunt) was diagnosed at a relatively younger age, explains Jessica Lee, MD, an assistant professor in the department of obstetrics and gynecology at University of Texas–Southwestern Medical Center in Dallas.\n\nOther risk factors include Eastern European or Ashkenazi Jewish background, and endometriosis, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Before becoming pregnant, atrisk women are often encouraged to speak to their family practitioners or gynecologists to determine if they are candidates for genetic testing says, Dr. Lee, adding that she often recommends that her pregnant patients consider forming a care team consisting of a gynecologist, gynecologic oncologist, and maternalfetal specialist if highrisk surveillance is required.\n\nAn Ovarian Cancer Diagnosis During Pregnancy\nMany of the signs and symptoms of adnexal masses and ovarian cancer are nonspecific. For example, abdominal bloating, abdominal and back pain, and changes in bladder and bowel function are also associated with pregnancy, says Sanaz Memarzadeh MD, professor and gynecologic cancer surgeon at UCLA Ronald Reagan Hospital in Los Angeles. According to Dr. Memarzadeh, these masses (called functional cysts) are often a normal part of pregnancy and disappear on their own by the second trimester. Many practitioners rely on a watchandwait strategy that includes a followup ultrasound in the second trimester to see if the mass has resolved.\n\nIf there is a suspicion that the mass may be cancerous, your doctor will likely refer you to a gynecologic oncologist for additional imaging (such as magnetic resonance imaging, or MRI, which can be safely used throughout pregnancy), staging, and if necessary, treatment. Women who live in more rural areas might be able to arrange initial telehealth appointments with a larger care team for some of these early decisions, notes Dr. Gray.\n\nWhy Early Detection Is Key\nAn advantage of earlier diagnosis is the potential to avoid unnecessary treatment and improve outcomes. Lee explains that treatment decisions are made on the basis of several factors, including the trimester of pregnancy, how quickly (or slowly) the tumor appears to be growing, if there is an indication that the tumor has spread (metastasized) beyond the ovaries, and gestation period.\n\nSometimes, minimally invasive, laparoscopic surgery is conducted to confirm diagnosis or to remove the tumor, but won’t be performed until after 16 weeks gestation and during the second trimester, when risks are the lowest to both the mother and fetus. If debulking surgery (removing as much of the tumor as possible) is indicated, it is often delayed until after birth, says Gray.\n\nIs Chemotherapy Safe When You’re Pregnant?\n\nEvery decision on how to proceed is made with two factors top of mind: the health of the mother and the baby. Pregnancies that involve maternal cancer are considered high risk, and mothers may need to be admitted to and followed throughout the pregnancy within a multidisciplinary care team obstetrical unit.\n\nIf the tumor cannot be completely removed by surgery, then your doctor and care team may recommend chemotherapy. Memarzedeh explains that chemotherapy can be safely administered during the second or third trimesters but if possible, might be delayed until after delivery. Decisions on timing (which also involve consultations with a maternalfetal medicine specialist) also may affect breastfeeding (so as to avoid passing toxins in milk to the newborn). However, if ample time has passed before delivery, breastfeeding can still be considered, Mamarzedeh says.\n\nFortunately, overall pregnancy outcomes for both the mother and fetus are similar to those seen in normal, healthy pregnancies, even when the pregnancy is high risk, according to a review published in the May 2017 issue of Best Practices Research Clinical Obstetrics  Gynecology Journal.\n\nOvarian Cancer Before Pregnancy and Fertility Preservation\nWhile it is perfectly safe to become pregnant if you’ve been diagnosed with ovarian cancer, fertility preservation strategies may be recommended. One option is to freeze eggs (cryopreservation) before starting chemotherapy and insert them by in vitro fertilization at a later time. This is associated with moderately good outcomes, says Marmazedeh, adding that about 40 percent of these women can achieve a successful pregnancy, and up to a third, successful deliveries.\n\nIn some cases, ovarian tissue can be frozen and then transplanted after cancer treatment, with successful delivery rates as high as 57 percent, according to a review published in February 2020 in the journal Acta Obstetricia et Gynecologica Scandinavica. In other cases, women may be able to opt for conservative treatment — removing one ovary with the cancer and the adjacent fallopian tube removed, which still provides her with the opportunity for pregnancy after treatment. All of these decisions are individual and made in coordination with the healthcare team and the expectant parent’s partner.\n\nOvarian cancer before or during pregnancy is relatively rare but incidence may increase as women continue to delay childbearing to older ages or as the population ages. When caught early — before or during pregnancy — the prognosis remains good for both the mother and child.\n\nThe bottom line is to know your family history and be prepared to discuss it or bring it up with your healthcare practitioner, especially as you explore your options for pregnancy and birth.</item>
        <item>Ovarian cancer is often caught in later, more advanced stages because there are often few symptoms early on in the course of the disease. Unfortunately, latestage ovarian cancer can cause pain and discomfort. And although treatment often helps alleviate pain, some therapies may actually add to the discomfort. If you find yourself in this situation, there are ways you can ease the pain.\n\nThe good news: Your ovarian cancer healthcare team will be very familiar with anything you face. And, in most cases, there are pain management techniques that can be tailormade to deal with most, if not all, situations.\n\nWhere Does Ovarian Cancer Cause Pain?\n\nIn its earliest stages, ovarian cancer may cause no symptoms or only mild ones. These symptoms include bloating, pelvic or abdominal pain, trouble eating or feeling full quickly, and urinary urgency, according to the National Ovarian Cancer Coalition. Ovarian cancer pain may also extend into the back, cause pain during sex, and, in advanced stages, cause leg pain.\n\nIs Ovarian Cancer Pain Constant, or Does It Come and Go?\n\nOvarian cancer pain can be tough to identify initially. “Women often report that they feel vague pelvic pain that feels like a little pressure. This pressure [generally] comes and goes,” says Marilyn Huang, MD, MS, codirector of translational gynecologic oncology research at the University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center.\n\n“The ovary moves based on our movement and relaxes when we aren’t as active, and so sometimes women feel better when they slow down,” she says. As such, discomfort waxes and wanes, which also makes seeking doctor care more complicated — it’s easy to convince yourself that it’s nothing or, if you don’t have “stabbing” or intense pain, that it’s no big deal at all.\n\nWhat Does Ovarian Cancer Pain Feel Like?\nWomen may experience different types of pain due to ovarian cancer: vague feelings of discomfort, sharp or shooting pains, a sensation of bloating, or dull and constant aches in the bones. Some women may not have any pain at all until their cancer is in a more advanced stage, says Carmel Cohen, MD, professor emeritus of obstetrics, gynecology, and reproductive science at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai in New York.\n\nAdvanced ovarian cancer can lead to issues that create pain because the tumor has grown. “The pain has to do either with invasion of bone, or intestinal obstruction and bowel dysfunction related to the expansion of the disease, which produces a blocked or kinked bowel,” says Cohen. “That’s usually a very late event in the course of ovarian cancer. It’s controlled with pain medication the same way that one would receive pain medication for any other significant amount of pain.”\n\nAre There Treatment and Medication Options to Help Manage Pain?\n\nWhen ovarian cancer is diagnosed, treatment of the disease is the first course of action to fight the cancer and try to alleviate pain. But disease management also includes pain medication to keep the pain under control.\n\nThe pain management strategy will depend on the symptoms. “A lot of patients do not have sharp, intense pain, so most do not require narcotics,” says Huang. Cohen strongly recommends that women talk about pain management with their healthcare providers early and often. If pain becomes considerable, they should not try to selfmedicate, he says. “They should consult a physician,” says Cohen, so that their doctor can determine the most appropriate way to treat and manage it.\n\nIn one study published in the March/April issue of Cancer Nursing, patients reported using 5 different physical and emotional coping strategies, including actively managing and planning for the pain, relaxation, and distraction. The authors conclude that women should try a range of strategies to cope with the pain in order to find what works for them.\n\nWhat If the Treatment Is Causing Pain?\n\nAt times, the treatments for ovarian cancer can seem worse than the disease. Surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy each of these carries with it a set of possible side effects and complications, not the least of which can be pain.\n\nPain management depends on the cause of pain, says Huang. For instance, if you had surgery to remove one or both ovaries (called an oophorectomy) or a hysterectomy, which involves removal of the uterus, then management includes treating postoperative pain, such as incisional pain. “This may include a combination of NSAIDs (nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs) and small doses of narcotics as needed,” says Huang.\n\nWomen with advanced disease may also need neoadjuvant therapies (therapies given before surgery), says Huang. This is done to reduce the size of the tumor and make it smaller and easier to remove. Chemotherapy may also be used after surgery to prevent its spread. However, chemotherapy can also cause neuropathic (nerve) pain.\nIn one study, 51 percent of women who received chemotherapy reported “a little” or “very much” peripheral neuropathy (tingling in hands and feet or numbness in fingers and toes) up to 12 years after treatment versus 27 percent of women who didn’t get chemo, per Gynecologic Oncology in December 2014. Neuropathic pain can be managed with medications like gabapentin, Lyrica (pregabalin), and Irenka (duloxetine), says Huang.</item>
        <item>Ovarian cancer is often caught in later, more advanced stages because there are often few symptoms early on in the course of the disease. Unfortunately, latestage ovarian cancer can cause pain and discomfort. And although treatment often helps alleviate pain, some therapies may actually add to the discomfort. If you find yourself in this situation, there are ways you can ease the pain.\n\nThe good news: Your ovarian cancer healthcare team will be very familiar with anything you face. And, in most cases, there are pain management techniques that can be tailormade to deal with most, if not all, situations.\n\nWhere Does Ovarian Cancer Cause Pain?\n\nIn its earliest stages, ovarian cancer may cause no symptoms or only mild ones. These symptoms include bloating, pelvic or abdominal pain, trouble eating or feeling full quickly, and urinary urgency, according to the National Ovarian Cancer Coalition. Ovarian cancer pain may also extend into the back, cause pain during sex, and, in advanced stages, cause leg pain.\n\nIs Ovarian Cancer Pain Constant, or Does It Come and Go?\n\nOvarian cancer pain can be tough to identify initially. “Women often report that they feel vague pelvic pain that feels like a little pressure. This pressure [generally] comes and goes,” says Marilyn Huang, MD, MS, codirector of translational gynecologic oncology research at the University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center.\n\n“The ovary moves based on our movement and relaxes when we aren’t as active, and so sometimes women feel better when they slow down,” she says. As such, discomfort waxes and wanes, which also makes seeking doctor care more complicated — it’s easy to convince yourself that it’s nothing or, if you don’t have “stabbing” or intense pain, that it’s no big deal at all.\n\nWhat Does Ovarian Cancer Pain Feel Like?\nWomen may experience different types of pain due to ovarian cancer: vague feelings of discomfort, sharp or shooting pains, a sensation of bloating, or dull and constant aches in the bones. Some women may not have any pain at all until their cancer is in a more advanced stage, says Carmel Cohen, MD, professor emeritus of obstetrics, gynecology, and reproductive science at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai in New York.\n\nAdvanced ovarian cancer can lead to issues that create pain because the tumor has grown. “The pain has to do either with invasion of bone, or intestinal obstruction and bowel dysfunction related to the expansion of the disease, which produces a blocked or kinked bowel,” says Cohen. “That’s usually a very late event in the course of ovarian cancer. It’s controlled with pain medication the same way that one would receive pain medication for any other significant amount of pain.”\n\nAre There Treatment and Medication Options to Help Manage Pain?\n\nWhen ovarian cancer is diagnosed, treatment of the disease is the first course of action to fight the cancer and try to alleviate pain. But disease management also includes pain medication to keep the pain under control.\n\nThe pain management strategy will depend on the symptoms. “A lot of patients do not have sharp, intense pain, so most do not require narcotics,” says Huang. Cohen strongly recommends that women talk about pain management with their healthcare providers early and often. If pain becomes considerable, they should not try to selfmedicate, he says. “They should consult a physician,” says Cohen, so that their doctor can determine the most appropriate way to treat and manage it.\n\nIn one study published in the March/April issue of Cancer Nursing, patients reported using 5 different physical and emotional coping strategies, including actively managing and planning for the pain, relaxation, and distraction. The authors conclude that women should try a range of strategies to cope with the pain in order to find what works for them.\n\nWhat If the Treatment Is Causing Pain?\n\nAt times, the treatments for ovarian cancer can seem worse than the disease. Surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy each of these carries with it a set of possible side effects and complications, not the least of which can be pain.\n\nPain management depends on the cause of pain, says Huang. For instance, if you had surgery to remove one or both ovaries (called an oophorectomy) or a hysterectomy, which involves removal of the uterus, then management includes treating postoperative pain, such as incisional pain. “This may include a combination of NSAIDs (nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs) and small doses of narcotics as needed,” says Huang.\n\nWomen with advanced disease may also need neoadjuvant therapies (therapies given before surgery), says Huang. This is done to reduce the size of the tumor and make it smaller and easier to remove. Chemotherapy may also be used after surgery to prevent its spread. However, chemotherapy can also cause neuropathic (nerve) pain.\nIn one study, 51 percent of women who received chemotherapy reported “a little” or “very much” peripheral neuropathy (tingling in hands and feet or numbness in fingers and toes) up to 12 years after treatment versus 27 percent of women who didn’t get chemo, per Gynecologic Oncology in December 2014. Neuropathic pain can be managed with medications like gabapentin, Lyrica (pregabalin), and Irenka (duloxetine), says Huang.</item>
        <item>Prenatal care is an important strategy for maintaining a healthy pregnancy and ensuring the best outcomes for a healthy baby. Screening is a routine part of this care; during the first trimester, it includes blood tests to detect chromosomal disorders such as Down syndrome and ultrasound to track the fetus’ growth and verify the approximate due date. Ultrasound imaging is also one of the most common ways that adnexal masses, growths that form on the organs and connective tissues around the ovaries, are discovered, according to the National Cancer Institute (NIH).\n\nAlthough adnexal masses are relatively common in pregnancy, 95 to 99 percent are benign (noncancerous) and disappear on their own, according to a study published November 2019 in the Journal of Ovarian Cancer Research. In fact, ovarian cancer is “exceedingly rare” during pregnancy (occurring in less than 1 percent), according to new research published in June 2020 by F1OOO Research. Still, both the discovery of a mass and a possible suspicion of cancer can be scary for expectant parents.\n\nWhat does it mean for the fetus’ health? Can the pregnancy be continued? And if you’ve had ovarian cancer previously, are you still able to become pregnant? Here’s what you need to know.\n\nKnow Your Ovarian Cancer Risk Most ovarian cancers actually start in the fallopian tubes, which serve as pathways to the uterus. Roughly 90 percent are epithelial, meaning that they originate in the cells residing on the outer lining of the ovaries. Ovarian cancers are characterized as benign, borderline (have low malignant potential), or malignant (cancerous), according to the American Cancer Society. \n\nFor women without a family history of ovarian cancer, risk increases with age, and more specifically, after menopause. The average age of most ovarian cancers is about 60, says Heidi Gray, MD, associate professor of gynecologic oncology at the University of Washington in Seattle.\n\nBut pregnancy in and of itself is not a risk factor, she says. In fact, previously carrying children to term before age 35 may offer extra protection against ovarian cancer, as does the use of oral contraceptives or breastfeeding, per the American Cancer Society. Most importantly, ovarian cancer during pregnancy is not commonly associated with a poorer prognosis, according to the International Network on Cancers infertility and pregnancy consensus guidelines, published October 2019 in the Annals of Oncology.\n\nA strong family history of ovarian cancer (or breast or colorectal cancer) increases overall ovarian cancer risk and increases the likelihood for harboring a pathogenic genetic mutation like BRCA1, or BRCA2, especially if a relative (especially mother, sister, or aunt) was diagnosed at a relatively younger age, explains Jessica Lee, MD, an assistant professor in the department of obstetrics and gynecology at University of Texas–Southwestern Medical Center in Dallas.\n\nOther risk factors include Eastern European or Ashkenazi Jewish background, and endometriosis, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Before becoming pregnant, atrisk women are often encouraged to speak to their family practitioners or gynecologists to determine if they are candidates for genetic testing says, Dr. Lee, adding that she often recommends that her pregnant patients consider forming a care team consisting of a gynecologist, gynecologic oncologist, and maternalfetal specialist if highrisk surveillance is required.\n\nAn Ovarian Cancer Diagnosis During Pregnancy\nMany of the signs and symptoms of adnexal masses and ovarian cancer are nonspecific. For example, abdominal bloating, abdominal and back pain, and changes in bladder and bowel function are also associated with pregnancy, says Sanaz Memarzadeh MD, professor and gynecologic cancer surgeon at UCLA Ronald Reagan Hospital in Los Angeles. According to Dr. Memarzadeh, these masses (called functional cysts) are often a normal part of pregnancy and disappear on their own by the second trimester. Many practitioners rely on a watchandwait strategy that includes a followup ultrasound in the second trimester to see if the mass has resolved.\n\nIf there is a suspicion that the mass may be cancerous, your doctor will likely refer you to a gynecologic oncologist for additional imaging (such as magnetic resonance imaging, or MRI, which can be safely used throughout pregnancy), staging, and if necessary, treatment. Women who live in more rural areas might be able to arrange initial telehealth appointments with a larger care team for some of these early decisions, notes Dr. Gray.\n\nWhy Early Detection Is Key\nAn advantage of earlier diagnosis is the potential to avoid unnecessary treatment and improve outcomes. Lee explains that treatment decisions are made on the basis of several factors, including the trimester of pregnancy, how quickly (or slowly) the tumor appears to be growing, if there is an indication that the tumor has spread (metastasized) beyond the ovaries, and gestation period.\n\nSometimes, minimally invasive, laparoscopic surgery is conducted to confirm diagnosis or to remove the tumor, but won’t be performed until after 16 weeks gestation and during the second trimester, when risks are the lowest to both the mother and fetus. If debulking surgery (removing as much of the tumor as possible) is indicated, it is often delayed until after birth, says Gray.\n\nIs Chemotherapy Safe When You’re Pregnant?\n\nEvery decision on how to proceed is made with two factors top of mind: the health of the mother and the baby. Pregnancies that involve maternal cancer are considered high risk, and mothers may need to be admitted to and followed throughout the pregnancy within a multidisciplinary care team obstetrical unit.\n\nIf the tumor cannot be completely removed by surgery, then your doctor and care team may recommend chemotherapy. Memarzedeh explains that chemotherapy can be safely administered during the second or third trimesters but if possible, might be delayed until after delivery. Decisions on timing (which also involve consultations with a maternalfetal medicine specialist) also may affect breastfeeding (so as to avoid passing toxins in milk to the newborn). However, if ample time has passed before delivery, breastfeeding can still be considered, Mamarzedeh says.\n\nFortunately, overall pregnancy outcomes for both the mother and fetus are similar to those seen in normal, healthy pregnancies, even when the pregnancy is high risk, according to a review published in the May 2017 issue of Best Practices Research Clinical Obstetrics  Gynecology Journal.\n\nOvarian Cancer Before Pregnancy and Fertility Preservation\nWhile it is perfectly safe to become pregnant if you’ve been diagnosed with ovarian cancer, fertility preservation strategies may be recommended. One option is to freeze eggs (cryopreservation) before starting chemotherapy and insert them by in vitro fertilization at a later time. This is associated with moderately good outcomes, says Marmazedeh, adding that about 40 percent of these women can achieve a successful pregnancy, and up to a third, successful deliveries.\n\nIn some cases, ovarian tissue can be frozen and then transplanted after cancer treatment, with successful delivery rates as high as 57 percent, according to a review published in February 2020 in the journal Acta Obstetricia et Gynecologica Scandinavica. In other cases, women may be able to opt for conservative treatment — removing one ovary with the cancer and the adjacent fallopian tube removed, which still provides her with the opportunity for pregnancy after treatment. All of these decisions are individual and made in coordination with the healthcare team and the expectant parent’s partner.\n\nOvarian cancer before or during pregnancy is relatively rare but incidence may increase as women continue to delay childbearing to older ages or as the population ages. When caught early — before or during pregnancy — the prognosis remains good for both the mother and child.\n\nThe bottom line is to know your family history and be prepared to discuss it or bring it up with your healthcare practitioner, especially as you explore your options for pregnancy and birth.</item>
        <item>Throughout the world, testosterone levels are decreasing, and most people don’t know this or understand the significance of this trend. It’s problematic on multiple levels — for reproduction, health and longevity, libido, and proper fetal development during pregnancy. While researching and writing our new book Count Down: How Our Modern World Is Threatening Sperm Counts, Altering Male and Female Reproductive Development, and Imperiling the Future of the Human Race, we discovered research showing not only that sperm counts and testosterone levels are declining, but they’re doing so in tandem and at an alarming rate of 1 percent per year in Western countries.\n\nAt first blush, this may not sound like a big deal, but it is. It adds up to more than a 10 percent decline per decade and more than a 50 percent drop over 50 years. Meanwhile, rates of testicular cancer and the prevalence of erectile dysfunction have been increasing at a similar rate, and so have miscarriage rates in the United States. It’s not a pretty picture.\n\nIts Not Just About Sperm Counts; Reproductive Health Is Also at Stake\nIt’s noteworthy that the use of testosterone replacement therapy has increased dramatically among younger men, many of whom are taking it to boost their energy and muscle mass. In fact, a study in the April 2017 issue of the Journal of Urology found that the use of testosterone replacement therapy had increased fourfold among men between the ages of 18 and 45 and threefold among older men from 2003 to 2013. What men don’t realize is that with testosterone replacement, a decline in sperm production occurs, so they’re working at crosspurposes with their best interests if they want to have children.\n\nThe Hormone Testosterone Plays a Role in Women’s Health as Well as Men’s Health\nPeople often think of testosterone as a “male” hormone, but girls and women also produce testosterone in their ovaries (in guys it’s made by the testes); however, women produce it in much smaller amounts than men do. In both sexes, the hormone affects energy levels, cognitive function, libido, and sexual function. When women’s lack of sexual desire is persistent and distressing, it’s called hypoactive sexual desire disorder, and according to a consensus statement in a 2019 issue of the NEJM Journal Watch Women’s Health, “Testosterone therapy is indicated only for postmenopausal women with hypoactive sexual desire disorder (HSDD), with evidence suggesting moderate therapeutic effects.” So clearly testosterone plays a crucial role in women’s sexual function, just as it does for men.\n\nFor women, there’s a sweet spot for testosterone levels at various stages of life. Too much or too little can send reproductive health and development in the wrong direction. For example, when a woman is pregnant, in order for her baby to develop properly, it needs to be exposed to the right amount of testosterone in the womb at the right time — it’s the Goldilocks conundrum in play.\nHere’s where things get tricky: Research has found that if a male fetus gets too little testosterone while in the womb, his genitals and his brain are likely to become less maletypical. By contrast, if a female fetus is exposed to too much testosterone in utero — perhaps because she has congenital adrenal hyperplasia, a genetic condition — her brain and genitals will be less femaletypical after she’s born. In other words, exposure to testosterone has the ability to push a developing fetus along the continuum between male and female. Once they’re born and start to grow up, these hormonal effects can influence the way children perceive themselves in terms of gender; what’s more, they can affect the kids’ activity preferences (playing with cars and trucks vs. dolls, for instance) and their style of play (roughandtumble vs. gentle, for example).\n\nIn addition, when girls and women have elevated levels of testosterone — as they do with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), which research suggests is increasing in incidence — they often have irregular periods, fertility challenges (including a higher rate of miscarriages), hair in unwanted places, acne, and excessive weight gain. And if they do have babies, these women’s baby girls are likely to have a higher body mass index (BMI), according to research published in April 2016 in Reproductive System and Sexual Disorders: Current Research.\n\nWhy Testosterone Levels Are Out of Whack\nNow that you know how testosterone levels affect women’s and men’s reproductive health, here’s the shocker: All the reproductive changes that have been occurring in recent years are too synchronous to be a coincidence. These changes are partly driven by poor lifestyle choices (such as smoking, binge drinking, and the like) but more so by the hundreds of chemicals that people are exposed to on a daily basis throughout the world, as we illustrate in our book.\n\nWill Unregulated Chemicals Continue to Compromise Fertility?\nNot only are these reproductive health changes interconnected, but they are largely driven by a common cause: the presence of endocrine disrupting chemicals (EDCs) in our world. These hormonehijacking chemicals — which include phthalates, bisphenol A, perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS), and flame retardants, among others — have become ubiquitous in our modern world. We ingest them in the air we breathe, our food and water, and the products we slather on our skin. That’s because they’re present in plastic water bottles and food packaging, nonstick cookware, electronic devices, cosmetic and personalcare products, cleaning supplies, and many other items that we use regularly.\n\nInside the human body they are playing havoc with the building blocks of sexual and reproductive development and reproductive health. These chemicals began being produced in increasing numbers after 1950, which is when sperm counts, testosterone levels, and fertility began to decline. Unbeknownst to many people, these chemicals are altering our testosterone levels, along with estrogen levels, and having detrimental effects on human reproductive health and development.\n\nMost people also don’t realize that these chemicals are largely unregulated: Unlike drugs, which must have a proven record of safety and effectiveness before they’re allowed onto the market, in the United States chemicals are presumed to be safe until they’re proven otherwise. This means that myriad chemicals that are used to manufacture an incredible array of consumer products are largely unregulated. In other words, we’ve been using each other and our unborn children as unwitting guinea pigs for EDC exposures — and this experiment is taking a toll on our reproductive health and potentially the future of the human race. \n\nShanna Swan, PhD, is one of the world’s leading environmental and reproductive epidemiologists and a professor of environmental medicine and public health at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai in New York City. She and Stacey Colino, a frequent contributor to Everyday Health, are coauthors of Count Down: How Our Modern World Is Threatening Sperm Counts, Altering Male and Female Reproductive Development, and Imperiling the Future of the Human Race, published in February 2021.</item>
        <item>Sexual health. For some people any sex topic is offlimits. But others, including the World Health Organization, consider sexual health an essential dimension of human health and wellbeing. From concern over how to have comfortable, enjoyable sex to questions about testing for sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) and their prevention, many important topics come under the broad umbrella of sexual health.\n\n“Sexual health is an essential and beneficial dimension of being human,” emphasizes Michael McGee, MEd, a certified sexual health educator and adjunct professor at Montclair State University in Montclair, N.J. “People have a right to sexual health, sexual health information including public policy that supports sexual health, and the right to pleasure.”\n\nIn addition to teaching and advocating about sexual health, McGee counsels individuals and couples on sexual health issues. He says the most common, fundamental question he encounters is, “Am I normal?”\n\nThis, he argues, is the best reason to be educated about sexual health: to have a realistic understanding of what sexual health is — what the wide range of “normal” is — as well as being better able to take care of your own health and pleasure and that of your partner.\n\nIncrease Your Sexual Health Awareness\n\nPremature ejaculation and a woman’s ability to achieve orgasm are topics that McGee says his clients often worry about — and appreciate learning how to manage. Other aspects of sexual health that people should be educated about include:\n\nSex basics. Understanding the cycle of desire, stimulation, and response improves sexual health, says McGee.\nReproductive issues. Sexual health is intimately related to reproduction. Birth control choices to prevent pregnancy and the steps couples need to take to have a healthy pregnancy are all aspects of sexual health.\nVaginal dryness. As women go through changes in their lives, such as pregnancy and childbirth or menopause, they may experience a lack of vagina lubrication. This makes sexual intercourse unpleasant, but there are solutions to this problem.\nLack of desire. A frequent source of conflict between couples, says McGee, is a “discrepancy in desire — one partner wants sex more often than the other.”\nErectile dysfunction. There are various physical and emotional reasons why men may not be able to achieve an erection for the duration of sexual intercourse.\nPhysical challenges. Physical impairment, health concerns, and other conditions may require creative problem solving in order to have sexual intercourse.\n\nSexual Health: Guarding Against Infection\n\nSex can be pleasurable, but it can also be risky. Sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) can be uncomfortable or painful; they can have severe, longterm effects that include the loss of fertility and have the potential to be lifethreatening. Learning about sexual health means learning about STDs:\n\nSTD identification. Learn about the signs and symptoms of STDs as well as the consequences of infection.\nPrevention. Taking steps to prevent the spread of STDs protects your health and the health of others.\nSTD testing. STD testing is a crucial part of your sexual health plan. Finding out whether you have an STD enables you to start treating the infection and protecting your sexual partners.\nLiving with an STD. Some STDs will be with you for life, such as hepatitis, herpes, and HIV/AIDS. For people living with STDs, sexual health encompasses coping with these infections over the long term.\nIntimate partner violence. Safety within sexual relationships continues to be a concern. Women may be particularly at risk for sexual violence.\n\nHow to Get Help for Intimate Issues.\n\nUnfortunately, many people wait a long time before seeking a solution to their sexual health concerns, notes McGee: “By the time they come to a professional, usually it has become a pressing need. And it is sometimes very difficult.” McGee recommends seeking help as soon as you have concerns rather than waiting and hoping the problem will go away.\n\nMcGee is certified by the American Association of Sexuality Educators, Counselors, and Therapists (AASECT) as a sexual health educator. Depending on the problems you want to resolve, your sexual health team could include a variety of health professionals, such as:\n\nPrimary care doctor\nObstetrician\ngynecologist\nUrologist\nPhysical therapist\nMental health professional\n\nWhether it’s knowledge about your body or information about treating a specific condition, take the right steps to get education and any counseling you might need to protect your sexual health.</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>